<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more            -->
<!-- contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with          -->
<!-- this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.           -->
<!-- The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0       -->
<!-- (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with          -->
<!-- the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at                          -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!--     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0                                -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software           -->
<!-- distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,             -->
<!-- WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.      -->
<!-- See the License for the specific language governing permissions and           -->
<!-- limitations under the License.                                                -->
<!-- ============================================================================= -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ActiveMQ_User_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="architecture">
    <title>Architecture</title>
    <para>In this section we will give an overview of the ActiveMQ high level architecture.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Core Architecture</title>
        <para>ActiveMQ core is designed simply as set of Plain Old Java Objects (POJOs) - we hope you
            like its clean-cut design.</para>
        <para>We've also designed it to have as few dependencies on external jars as possible. In
            fact, ActiveMQ core has only one jar dependency, netty.jar,
            other than the standard JDK classes! This is because we use some of the netty buffer classes
        internally.</para>
        <para>This allows ActiveMQ to be easily embedded in your own project, or instantiated in any
            dependency injection framework such as JBoss Microcontainer, Spring or Google
            Guice.</para>
        <para>Each ActiveMQ server has its own ultra high performance persistent journal, which it
            uses for message and other persistence.</para>
        <para>Using a high performance journal allows outrageous persistence message performance,
            something not achievable when using a relational database for persistence.</para>
        <para>ActiveMQ clients, potentially on different physical machines interact with the ActiveMQ
            server. ActiveMQ currently provides two APIs for messaging at the client side:</para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Core client API. This is a simple intuitive Java API that allows the full
                        set of messaging functionality without some of the complexities of
                        JMS.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>JMS client API. The standard JMS API is available at the client
                        side.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>JMS semantics are implemented by a thin JMS facade layer on the client side.</para>
        <para>The ActiveMQ server does not speak JMS and in fact does not know anything about JMS,
            it is a protocol agnostic messaging server designed to be used with multiple different
            protocols.</para>
        <para>When a user uses the JMS API on the client side, all JMS interactions are translated
            into operations on the ActiveMQ core client API before being transferred over the wire
            using the ActiveMQ wire format.</para>
        <para>The server always just deals with core API interactions.</para>
        <para>A schematic illustrating this relationship is shown in figure 3.1 below:</para>
        <para>
            <graphic fileref="images/architecture1.jpg" align="center"/>
        </para>
        <para>Figure 3.1 shows two user applications interacting with a ActiveMQ server. User
            Application 1 is using the JMS API, while User Application 2 is using the core client
            API directly.</para>
        <para>You can see from the diagram that the JMS API is implemented by a thin facade layer on
            the client side.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>ActiveMQ embedded in your own application</title>
        <para>ActiveMQ core is designed as a set of simple POJOs so if you have an application that
            requires messaging functionality internally but you don't want to expose that as a
            ActiveMQ server you can directly instantiate and embed ActiveMQ servers in your own
            application.</para>
        <para>For more information on embedding ActiveMQ, see <xref linkend="embedding-activemq"
            />.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>ActiveMQ integrated with a JEE application server</title>
        <para>ActiveMQ provides its own fully functional Java Connector Architecture (JCA) adaptor
            which enables it to be integrated easily into any JEE compliant application server or
            servlet engine.</para>
        <para>JEE application servers provide Message Driven Beans (MDBs), which are a special type
            of Enterprise Java Beans (EJBs) that can process messages from sources such as JMS
            systems or mail systems.</para>
        <para>Probably the most common use of an MDB is to consume messages from a JMS messaging
            system.</para>
        <para>According to the JEE specification, a JEE application server uses a JCA adapter to
            integrate with a JMS messaging system so it can consume messages for MDBs.</para>
        <para>However, the JCA adapter is not only used by the JEE application server for <emphasis
                role="italic">consuming</emphasis> messages via MDBs, it is also used when sending
            message to the JMS messaging system e.g. from inside an EJB or servlet.</para>
        <para>When integrating with a JMS messaging system from inside a JEE application server it
            is always recommended that this is done via a JCA adaptor. In fact, communicating with a
            JMS messaging system directly, without using JCA would be illegal according to the JEE
            specification.</para>
        <para>The application server's JCA service provides extra functionality such as connection
            pooling and automatic transaction enlistment, which are desirable when using messaging,
            say, from inside an EJB. It is possible to talk to a JMS messaging system directly from
            an EJB, MDB or servlet without going through a JCA adapter, but this is not recommended
            since you will not be able to take advantage of the JCA features, such as caching of JMS
            sessions, which can result in poor performance.</para>
        <para>Figure 3.2 below shows a JEE application server integrating with a ActiveMQ server via
            the ActiveMQ JCA adaptor. Note that all communication between EJB sessions or entity
            beans and Message Driven beans go through the adaptor and not directly to
            ActiveMQ.</para>
        <para>The large arrow with the prohibited sign shows an EJB session bean talking directly to
            the ActiveMQ server. This is not recommended as you'll most likely end up creating a new
            connection and session every time you want to interact from the EJB, which is an
            anti-pattern.</para>
        <para>
            <graphic fileref="images/architecture2.jpg"/>
        </para>
        <para>For more information on using the JCA adaptor, please see <xref
                linkend="appserver-integration"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>ActiveMQ stand-alone server</title>
        <para>ActiveMQ can also be deployed as a stand-alone server. This means a fully independent
            messaging server not dependent on a JEE application server.</para>
        <para>The standard stand-alone messaging server configuration comprises a core messaging
            server, a JMS service and a JNDI service.</para>
        <para>The role of the JMS Service is to deploy any JMS Queue, Topic and ConnectionFactory
            instances from any server side <literal>activemq-jms.xml</literal> configuration files.
            It also provides a simple management API for creating and destroying Queues, Topics and
            ConnectionFactory instances which can be accessed via JMX or the connection. It is a
            separate service to the ActiveMQ core server, since the core server is JMS agnostic. If
            you don't want to deploy any JMS Queue, Topic or ConnectionFactory instances via server
            side XML configuration and don't require a JMS management API on the server side then
            you can disable this service.</para>
        <para>We also include a JNDI server since JNDI is a common requirement when using JMS to
            lookup Queues, Topics and ConnectionFactory instances. If you do not require JNDI then
            this service can also be disabled. ActiveMQ allows you to programmatically create JMS and
            core objects directly on the client side as opposed to looking them up from JNDI, so a
            JNDI server is not always a requirement.</para>
        <para>The stand-alone server configuration uses JBoss Microcontainer to instantiate and
            enforce dependencies between the components. JBoss Microcontainer is a very lightweight
            POJO bootstrapper.</para>
        <para>The stand-alone server architecture is shown in figure 3.3 below:</para>
        <para>
            <graphic fileref="images/architecture3.jpg"/>
        </para>
        <para>For more information on server configuration files see <xref
                linkend="server.configuration"/>. $ </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
