<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<!-- Copyright © 2009 Red Hat, Inc. and others.                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- The text of and illustrations in this document are licensed by Red Hat under  -->
<!-- a Creative Commons Attribution–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license ("CC-BY-SA"). -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- An explanation of CC-BY-SA is available at                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!--            http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/.                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- In accordance with CC-BY-SA, if you distribute this document or an adaptation -->
<!-- of it, you must provide the URL for the original version.                     -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- Red Hat, as the licensor of this document, waives the right to enforce,       -->
<!-- and agrees not to assert, Section 4d of CC-BY-SA to the fullest extent        -->
<!-- permitted by applicable law.                                                  -->
<!-- ============================================================================= -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ActiveMQ_User_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="client-reconnection">
    <title>Client Reconnection and Session Reattachment</title>
    <para>ActiveMQ clients can be configured to automatically reconnect or re-attach to the server in
        the event that a failure is detected in the connection between the client and the server. </para>
    <section>
        <title>100% Transparent session re-attachment</title>
        <para>If the failure was due to some transient failure such as a temporary network failure,
            and the target server was not restarted, then the sessions will still be existent on the
            server, assuming the client hasn't been disconnected for more than connection-ttl <xref
                linkend="connection-ttl"/>.</para>
        <para>In this scenario, ActiveMQ will automatically re-attach the client sessions to the
            server sessions when the connection reconnects. This is done 100% transparently and the
            client can continue exactly as if nothing had happened.</para>
        <para>The way this works is as follows:</para>
        <para>As ActiveMQ clients send commands to their servers they store each sent command in an
            in-memory buffer. In the case that connection failure occurs and the client subsequently
            reattaches to the same server, as part of the reattachment protocol the server informs
            the client during reattachment with the id of the last command it successfully received
            from that client.</para>
        <para>If the client has sent more commands than were received before failover it can replay
            any sent commands from its buffer so that the client and server can reconcile their
            states.</para>
        <para>The size of this buffer is configured by the <literal>ConfirmationWindowSize</literal>
            parameter, when the server has received <literal>ConfirmationWindowSize</literal> bytes
            of commands and processed them it will send back a command confirmation to the client,
            and the client can then free up space in the buffer.</para>
        <para>If you are using JMS and you're using the JMS service on the server to load your JMS
            connection factory instances into JNDI then this parameter can be configured in <literal
                >activemq-jms.xml</literal> using the element <literal
                >confirmation-window-size</literal> a. If you're using JMS but not using JNDI then
            you can set these values directly on the <literal>ActiveMQConnectionFactory</literal>
            instance using the appropriate setter method.</para>
        <para>If you're using the core API you can set these values directly on the <literal
                >ServerLocator</literal> instance using the appropriate setter method.</para>
        <para>The window is specified in bytes.</para>
        <para>Setting this parameter to <literal>-1</literal> disables any buffering and prevents
            any re-attachment from occurring, forcing reconnect instead. The default value for this
            parameter is <literal>-1</literal>. (Which means by default no auto re-attachment will occur)</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Session reconnection</title>
        <para>Alternatively, the server might have actually been restarted after crashing or being
            stopped. In this case any sessions will no longer be existent on the server and it won't
            be possible to 100% transparently re-attach to them.</para>
        <para>In this case, ActiveMQ will automatically reconnect the connection and <emphasis
                role="italic">recreate</emphasis> any sessions and consumers on the server
            corresponding to the sessions and consumers on the client. This process is exactly the
            same as what happens during failover onto a backup server.</para>
        <para>Client reconnection is also used internally by components such as core bridges to
            allow them to reconnect to their target servers.</para>
        <para>Please see the section on failover <xref linkend="ha.automatic.failover"/> to get a
            full understanding of how transacted and non-transacted sessions are reconnected during
            failover/reconnect and what you need to do to maintain <emphasis role="italic">once and
                only once </emphasis>delivery guarantees.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Configuring reconnection/reattachment attributes</title>
        <para>Client reconnection is configured using the following parameters:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>retry-interval</literal>. This optional parameter determines the
                    period in milliseconds between subsequent reconnection attempts, if the
                    connection to the target server has failed. The default value is <literal
                        >2000</literal> milliseconds.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>retry-interval-multiplier</literal>. This optional parameter
                    determines determines a multiplier to apply to the time since the last retry to
                    compute the time to the next retry.</para>
                <para>This allows you to implement an <emphasis>exponential backoff</emphasis>
                    between retry attempts.</para>
                <para>Let's take an example:</para>
                <para>If we set <literal>retry-interval</literal> to <literal>1000</literal> ms and
                    we set <literal>retry-interval-multiplier</literal> to <literal>2.0</literal>,
                    then, if the first reconnect attempt fails, we will wait <literal>1000</literal>
                    ms then <literal>2000</literal> ms then <literal>4000</literal> ms between
                    subsequent reconnection attempts.</para>
                <para>The default value is <literal>1.0</literal> meaning each reconnect attempt is
                    spaced at equal intervals.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>max-retry-interval</literal>. This optional parameter determines the
                    maximum retry interval that will be used. When setting <literal
                        >retry-interval-multiplier</literal> it would otherwise be possible that
                    subsequent retries exponentially increase to ridiculously large values. By
                    setting this parameter you can set an upper limit on that value. The default
                    value is <literal>2000</literal> milliseconds.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>reconnect-attempts</literal>. This optional parameter determines the
                    total number of reconnect attempts to make before giving up and shutting down. A
                    value of <literal>-1</literal> signifies an unlimited number of attempts. The
                    default value is <literal>0</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>If you're using JMS, and you're using the JMS Service on the server to load your JMS
            connection factory instances directly into JNDI, then you can specify these parameters
            in the xml configuration in <literal>activemq-jms.xml</literal>, for example:</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;connection-factory name="ConnectionFactory">
   &lt;connectors>
      &lt;connector-ref connector-name="netty"/>
   &lt;/connectors>
   &lt;entries>
      &lt;entry name="ConnectionFactory"/>
      &lt;entry name="XAConnectionFactory"/>
   &lt;/entries>
   &lt;retry-interval>1000&lt;/retry-interval>
   &lt;retry-interval-multiplier>1.5&lt;/retry-interval-multiplier>
   &lt;max-retry-interval>60000&lt;/max-retry-interval>
   &lt;reconnect-attempts>1000&lt;/reconnect-attempts>
&lt;/connection-factory></programlisting>
        <para>If you're using JMS, but instantiating your JMS connection factory directly, you can
            specify the parameters using the appropriate setter methods on the <literal
                >ActiveMQConnectionFactory</literal> immediately after creating it.</para>
        <para>If you're using the core API and instantiating the <literal
                >ServerLocator</literal> instance directly you can also specify the
            parameters using the appropriate setter methods on the <literal
                >ServerLocator</literal> immediately after creating it.</para>
        <para>If your client does manage to reconnect but the session is no longer available on the
            server, for instance if the server has been restarted or it has timed out, then the
            client won't be able to re-attach, and any <literal>ExceptionListener</literal> or
                <literal>FailureListener</literal> instances registered on the connection or session
            will be called.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="client-reconnection.exceptionlistener">
        <title>ExceptionListeners and SessionFailureListeners</title>
        <para>Please note, that when a client reconnects or re-attaches, any registered JMS <literal
                >ExceptionListener</literal> or core API <literal>SessionFailureListener</literal>
            will be called.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
