<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<!-- Copyright © 2009 Red Hat, Inc. and others.                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- The text of and illustrations in this document are licensed by Red Hat under  -->
<!-- a Creative Commons Attribution–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license ("CC-BY-SA"). -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- An explanation of CC-BY-SA is available at                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!--            http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/.                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- In accordance with CC-BY-SA, if you distribute this document or an adaptation -->
<!-- of it, you must provide the URL for the original version.                     -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- Red Hat, as the licensor of this document, waives the right to enforce,       -->
<!-- and agrees not to assert, Section 4d of CC-BY-SA to the fullest extent        -->
<!-- permitted by applicable law.                                                  -->
<!-- ============================================================================= -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "HornetQ_User_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="configuring-transports">
    <title>Configuring the Transport</title>
    <para>HornetQ has a fully pluggable and highly flexible transport layer and defines its own
        Service Provider Interface (SPI) to make plugging in a new transport provider relatively
        straightforward.</para>
    <para>In this chapter we'll describe the concepts required for understanding HornetQ transports
        and where and how they're configured.</para>
    <section id="configuring-transports.acceptors">
        <title>Understanding Acceptors</title>
        <para>One of the most important concepts in HornetQ transports is the
                <emphasis>acceptor</emphasis>. Let's dive straight in and take a look at an acceptor
            defined in xml in the configuration file <literal
            >hornetq-configuration.xml</literal>.</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;acceptors>
   &lt;acceptor name="netty">
      &lt;factory-class>
         org.apache.activemq6.core.remoting.impl.netty.NettyAcceptorFactory
      &lt;/factory-class>
      &lt;param key="port" value="5446"/>
   &lt;/acceptor>
&lt;/acceptors></programlisting>
        <para>Acceptors are always defined inside an <literal>acceptors</literal> element. There can
            be one or more acceptors defined in the <literal>acceptors</literal> element. There's no
            upper limit to the number of acceptors per server.</para>
        <para>Each acceptor defines a way in which connections can be made to the HornetQ
            server.</para>
        <para>In the above example we're defining an acceptor that uses <ulink
                url="http://jboss.org/netty">Netty</ulink> to listen for connections at port
                <literal>5446</literal>. </para>
        <para>The <literal>acceptor</literal> element contains a sub-element <literal
                >factory-class</literal>, this element defines the factory used to create acceptor
            instances. In this case we're using Netty to listen for connections so we use the Netty
            implementation of an <literal>AcceptorFactory</literal> to do this. Basically, the
                <literal>factory-class</literal> element determines which pluggable transport we're
            going to use to do the actual listening.</para>
        <para>The <literal>acceptor</literal> element can also be configured with zero or more
                <literal>param</literal> sub-elements. Each <literal>param</literal> element defines
            a key-value pair. These key-value pairs are used to configure the specific transport,
            the set of valid key-value pairs depends on the specific transport be used and are
            passed straight through to the underlying transport.</para>
        <para>Examples of key-value pairs for a particular transport would be, say, to configure the
            IP address to bind to, or the port to listen at.</para>
        <para>Note that unlike versions before 2.4 an Acceptor can now support multiple protocols. By default this will
            be all available protocols but can be limited by either the now deprecated <literal>protocol</literal> param or
        by setting a comma seperated list to the newly added <literal>protocols</literal> parameter.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="configuring-transports.connectors">
        <title>Understanding Connectors</title>
        <para>Whereas acceptors are used on the server to define how we accept connections,
            connectors are used by a client to define how it connects to a server.</para>
        <para>Let's look at a connector defined in our <literal>hornetq-configuration.xml</literal>
            file:</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;connectors>
   &lt;connector name="netty">
      &lt;factory-class>
         org.apache.activemq6.core.remoting.impl.netty.NettyConnectorFactory
      &lt;/factory-class>
      &lt;param key="port" value="5446"/>
   &lt;/connector>
&lt;/connectors></programlisting>
        <para>Connectors can be defined inside a <literal>connectors</literal> element. There can be
            one or more connectors defined in the <literal>connectors</literal> element. There's no
            upper limit to the number of connectors per server.</para>
        <para>You make ask yourself, if connectors are used by the <emphasis>client</emphasis> to
            make connections then why are they defined on the <emphasis>server</emphasis>? There are
            a couple of reasons for this:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Sometimes the server acts as a client itself when it connects to another
                    server, for example when one server is bridged to another, or when a server
                    takes part in a cluster. In this cases the server needs to know how to connect
                    to other servers. That's defined by <emphasis>connectors</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If you're using JMS and the server side JMS service to instantiate JMS
                    ConnectionFactory instances and bind them in JNDI, then when creating the
                        <literal>HornetQConnectionFactory</literal> it needs to know what server
                    that connection factory will create connections to.</para>
                <para>That's defined by the <literal>connector-ref</literal> element in the <literal
                        >hornetq-jms.xml</literal> file on the server side. Let's take a look at a
                    snipped from a <literal>hornetq-jms.xml</literal> file that shows a JMS
                    connection factory that references our netty connector defined in our <literal
                        >hornetq-configuration.xml</literal> file:</para>
                <programlisting>
&lt;connection-factory name="ConnectionFactory">
   &lt;connectors>
      &lt;connector-ref connector-name="netty"/>
   &lt;/connectors>
   &lt;entries>
      &lt;entry name="ConnectionFactory"/>
      &lt;entry name="XAConnectionFactory"/>
   &lt;/entries>
&lt;/connection-factory></programlisting>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="configuring-transports.client.side">
        <title>Configuring the transport directly from the client side.</title>
        <para>How do we configure a core <literal>ClientSessionFactory</literal> with the
            information that it needs to connect with a server?</para>
        <para>Connectors are also used indirectly when directly configuring a core <literal
                >ClientSessionFactory</literal> to directly talk to a server. Although in this case
            there's no need to define such a connector in the server side configuration, instead we
            just create the parameters and tell the <literal>ClientSessionFactory</literal> which
            connector factory to use.</para>
        <para>Here's an example of creating a <literal>ClientSessionFactory</literal> which will
            connect directly to the acceptor we defined earlier in this chapter, it uses the
            standard Netty TCP transport and will try and connect on port 5446 to localhost
            (default):</para>
        <programlisting>
Map&lt;String, Object> connectionParams = new HashMap&lt;String, Object>();

connectionParams.put(org.apache.activemq6.core.remoting.impl.netty.TransportConstants.PORT_PROP_NAME,
                    5446);

TransportConfiguration transportConfiguration =
    new TransportConfiguration(
    "org.apache.activemq6.core.remoting.impl.netty.NettyConnectorFactory",
    connectionParams);

ServerLocator locator = HornetQClient.createServerLocatorWithoutHA(transportConfiguration);

ClientSessionFactory sessionFactory = locator.createClientSessionFactory();

ClientSession session = sessionFactory.createSession(...);

etc</programlisting>
        <para>Similarly, if you're using JMS, you can configure the JMS connection factory directly
            on the client side without having to define a connector on the server side or define a
            connection factory in <literal>hornetq-jms.xml</literal>:</para>
        <programlisting>
Map&lt;String, Object> connectionParams = new HashMap&lt;String, Object>();

connectionParams.put(org.apache.activemq6.core.remoting.impl.netty.TransportConstants.PORT_PROP_NAME, 5446);

TransportConfiguration transportConfiguration =
    new TransportConfiguration(
    "org.apache.activemq6.core.remoting.impl.netty.NettyConnectorFactory",
    connectionParams);

ConnectionFactory connectionFactory = HornetQJMSClient.createConnectionFactoryWithoutHA(JMSFactoryType.CF, transportConfiguration);

Connection jmsConnection = connectionFactory.createConnection();

etc</programlisting>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Configuring the Netty transport</title>
        <para>Out of the box, HornetQ currently uses <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/netty/"
                >Netty</ulink>, a high performance low level network library.</para>
        <para>Our Netty transport can be configured in several different ways; to use old (blocking)
            Java IO, or NIO (non-blocking), also to use straightforward TCP sockets, SSL, or to
            tunnel over HTTP or HTTPS..</para>
        <para>We believe this caters for the vast majority of transport requirements.</para>
        <section id="configuring-transports.single-port">
            <title>Single Port Support</title>
            <para>As of version 2.4 HornetQ now supports using a single port for all protocols, HornetQ will automatically
            detect which protocol is being used CORE, AMQP, STOMP or OPENWIRE and use the appropriate HornetQ handler. It will also detect
            whether protocols such as HTTP or Web Sockets are being used and also use the appropriate decoders</para>
            <para>It is possible to limit which protocols are supported by using the <literal>protocols</literal> parameter
            on the Acceptor like so:</para>
            <programlisting>
    &lt;param key="protocols" value="CORE,AMQP"/>
            </programlisting>
            <note><para>The <literal>protocol</literal> parameter is now deprecated</para></note>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Configuring Netty TCP</title>
            <para>Netty TCP is a simple unencrypted TCP sockets based transport. Netty TCP can be
                configured to use old blocking Java IO or non blocking Java NIO. We recommend you
                use the Java NIO on the server side for better scalability with many concurrent
                connections. However using Java old IO can sometimes give you better latency than
                NIO when you're not so worried about supporting many thousands of concurrent
                connections. </para>
            <para>If you're running connections across an untrusted network please bear in mind this
                transport is unencrypted. You may want to look at the SSL or HTTPS
                configurations.</para>
            <para>With the Netty TCP transport all connections are initiated from the client side.
                I.e. the server does not initiate any connections to the client. This works well
                with firewall policies that typically only allow connections to be initiated in one
                direction.</para>
            <para>All the valid Netty transport keys are defined in the class <literal
                    >org.apache.activemq6.core.remoting.impl.netty.TransportConstants</literal>. Most
                parameters can be used either with acceptors or connectors, some only work with
                acceptors. The following parameters can be used to configure Netty for simple
                TCP:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>use-nio</literal>. If this is <literal>true</literal> then Java
                        non blocking NIO will be used. If set to <literal>false</literal> then old
                        blocking Java IO will be used.</para>
                    <para>If you require the server to handle many concurrent connections, we highly
                        recommend that you use non blocking Java NIO. Java NIO does not maintain a
                        thread per connection so can scale to many more concurrent connections than
                        with old blocking IO. If you don't require the server to handle many
                        concurrent connections, you might get slightly better performance by using
                        old (blocking) IO. The default value for this property is <literal
                            >false</literal> on the server side and <literal>false</literal> on the
                        client side.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>host</literal>. This specifies the host name or IP address to
                        connect to (when configuring a connector) or to listen on (when configuring
                        an acceptor). The default value for this property is <literal
                            >localhost</literal>. When configuring acceptors, multiple hosts or IP
                        addresses can be specified by separating them with commas. It is also
                        possible to specify <code>0.0.0.0</code> to accept connection from all the
                        host's network interfaces. It's not valid to specify multiple addresses when
                        specifying the host for a connector; a connector makes a connection to one
                        specific address.</para>
                    <note>
                        <para>Don't forget to specify a host name or IP address! If you want your
                            server able to accept connections from other nodes you must specify a
                            hostname or IP address at which the acceptor will bind and listen for
                            incoming connections. The default is localhost which of course is not
                            accessible from remote nodes!</para>
                    </note>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>port</literal>. This specified the port to connect to (when
                        configuring a connector) or to listen on (when configuring an acceptor). The
                        default value for this property is <literal>5445</literal>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>tcp-no-delay</literal>. If this is <literal>true</literal> then
                            <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nagle%27s_algorithm">Nagle's
                            algorithm</ulink> will be disabled. This is a
                            <ulink url="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/technotes/guides/net/socketOpt.html">Java (client) socket option</ulink>. The default value for this property is <literal>true</literal>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>tcp-send-buffer-size</literal>. This parameter determines the
                        size of the TCP send buffer in bytes. The default value for this property is
                            <literal>32768</literal> bytes (32KiB).</para>
                    <para>TCP buffer sizes should be tuned according to the bandwidth and latency of
                        your network. Here's a good link that explains the theory behind <ulink
                            url="http://www-didc.lbl.gov/TCP-tuning/">this</ulink>.</para>
                    <para>In summary TCP send/receive buffer sizes should be calculated as:</para>
                    <programlisting>
buffer_size = bandwidth * RTT.</programlisting>
                    <para>Where bandwidth is in <emphasis>bytes per second</emphasis> and network
                        round trip time (RTT) is in seconds. RTT can be easily measured using the
                            <literal>ping</literal> utility.</para>
                    <para>For fast networks you may want to increase the buffer sizes from the
                        defaults.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>tcp-receive-buffer-size</literal>. This parameter determines the
                        size of the TCP receive buffer in bytes. The default value for this property
                        is <literal>32768</literal> bytes (32KiB).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>batch-delay</literal>. Before writing packets to the transport,
                        HornetQ can be configured to batch up writes for a maximum of <literal
                            >batch-delay</literal> milliseconds. This can increase overall
                        throughput for very small messages. It does so at the expense of an increase
                        in average latency for message transfer. The default value for this property
                        is <literal>0</literal> ms.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>direct-deliver</literal>. When a message arrives on the server
                        and is delivered to waiting consumers, by default, the delivery is done on
                        the same thread as that on which the message arrived. This gives good latency
                        in environments with relatively small messages and a small number of consumers,
                        but at the cost of overall throughput and scalability - especially on multi-core
                        machines. If you want the lowest latency and a possible reduction in throughput
                        then you can use the default value for <literal>direct-deliver</literal> (i.e.
                        true). If you are willing to take some small extra hit on latency but want the
                        highest throughput set <literal>direct-deliver</literal> to <literal>false
                        </literal>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>nio-remoting-threads</literal>. When configured to use NIO,
                        HornetQ will, by default, use a number of threads equal to three times the
                        number of cores (or hyper-threads) as reported by <literal
                            >Runtime.getRuntime().availableProcessors()</literal> for processing
                        incoming packets. If you want to override this value, you can set the number
                        of threads by specifying this parameter. The default value for this
                        parameter is <literal>-1</literal> which means use the value from <literal
                            >Runtime.getRuntime().availableProcessors()</literal> * 3.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>local-address</literal>. When configured a Netty Connector it is possible to specify
                        which local address the client will use when connecting to the remote address. This is typically used
                        in the Application Server or when running Embedded to control which address is used for outbound
                        connections. If the local-address is not set then the connector will use any local address available</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>local-port</literal>. When configured a Netty Connector it is possible to specify
                        which local port the client will use when connecting to the remote address. This is typically used
                        in the Application Server or when running Embedded to control which port is used for outbound
                        connections. If the local-port default is used, which is 0, then the connector will let the
                       system pick up an ephemeral port. valid ports are 0 to 65535</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Configuring Netty SSL</title>
            <para>Netty SSL is similar to the Netty TCP transport but it provides additional
                security by encrypting TCP connections using the Secure Sockets Layer SSL</para>
            <para>Please see the examples for a full working example of using Netty SSL.</para>
            <para>Netty SSL uses all the same properties as Netty TCP but adds the following
                additional properties:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>ssl-enabled</literal></para>
                    <para>Must be <literal>true</literal> to enable SSL. Default is <literal>false</literal>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>key-store-path</literal></para>
                    <para>When used on an <literal>acceptor</literal> this is the path to the SSL key
                        store on the server which holds the server's certificates (whether self-signed
                        or signed by an authority).</para>
                    <para>When used on a <literal>connector</literal> this is the path to the client-side
                        SSL key store which holds the client certificates. This is only relevant
                        for a <literal>connector</literal> if you are using 2-way SSL (i.e. mutual
                        authentication). Although this value is configured on the server, it is
                        downloaded and used by the client. If the client needs to use a different path
                        from that set on the server then it can override the server-side setting by either
                        using the customary "javax.net.ssl.keyStore" system property or the HornetQ-specific
                        "org.apache.activemq6.ssl.keyStore" system property. The HornetQ-specific system property
                        is useful if another component on client is already making use of the standard, Java
                        system property.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>key-store-password</literal></para>
                    <para>When used on an <literal>acceptor</literal> this is the password for the
                        server-side keystore.</para>
                    <para>When used on a <literal>connector</literal> this is the password for the
                        client-side keystore.  This is only relevant for a <literal>connector</literal>
                        if you are using 2-way SSL (i.e. mutual authentication). Although this value can
                        be configured on the server, it is downloaded and used by the client.  If the client
                        needs to use a different password from that set on the server then it can override
                        the server-side setting by either using the customary "javax.net.ssl.keyStorePassword"
                        system property or the HornetQ-specific "org.apache.activemq6.ssl.keyStorePassword" system
                        property. The HornetQ-specific system property is useful if another component on client
                        is already making use of the standard, Java system property.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>trust-store-path</literal></para>
                    <para>When used on an <literal>acceptor</literal> this is the path to the server-side
                        SSL key store that holds the keys of all the clients that the server trusts.  This
                        is only relevant for an <literal>acceptor</literal> if you are using 2-way SSL
                        (i.e. mutual authentication).</para>
                    <para>When used on a <literal>connector</literal> this is the path to the client-side
                        SSL key store which holds the public keys of all the servers that the client
                        trusts. Although this value can be configured on the server, it is downloaded and
                        used by the client.  If the client needs to use a different path
                        from that set on the server then it can override the server-side setting by either
                        using the customary "javax.net.ssl.trustStore" system property or the HornetQ-specific
                        "org.apache.activemq6.ssl.trustStore" system property. The HornetQ-specific system property
                        is useful if another component on client is already making use of the standard, Java
                        system property.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>trust-store-password</literal></para>
                    <para>When used on an <literal>acceptor</literal> this is the password for the
                        server-side trust store.  This is only relevant for an <literal>acceptor</literal>
                        if you are using 2-way SSL (i.e. mutual authentication).</para>
                    <para>When used on a <literal>connector</literal> this is the password for the
                        client-side truststore. Although this value can be configured on the server, it is
                        downloaded and used by the client.   If the client
                        needs to use a different password from that set on the server then it can override
                        the server-side setting by either using the customary "javax.net.ssl.trustStorePassword"
                        system property or the HornetQ-specific "org.apache.activemq6.ssl.trustStorePassword" system
                        property. The HornetQ-specific system property is useful if another component on client
                        is already making use of the standard, Java system property.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>enabled-cipher-suites</literal></para>
                    <para>Whether used on an <literal>acceptor</literal> or <literal>connector</literal> this is a
                        comma separated list of cipher suites used for SSL communication. The default value is
                        <literal>null</literal> which means the JVM's default will be used.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>enabled-protocols</literal></para>
                    <para>Whether used on an <literal>acceptor</literal> or <literal>connector</literal> this is a
                        comma separated list of protocols used for SSL communication. The default value is
                        <literal>null</literal> which means the JVM's default will be used.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>need-client-auth</literal></para>
                    <para>This property is only for an <literal>acceptor</literal>. It tells a client connecting to this
                        acceptor that 2-way SSL is required. Valid values are <literal>true</literal> or
                        <literal>false</literal>. Default is <literal>false</literal>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Configuring Netty HTTP</title>
            <para>Netty HTTP tunnels packets over the HTTP protocol. It can be useful in scenarios
                where firewalls only allow HTTP traffic to pass.</para>
            <para>Please see the examples for a full working example of using Netty HTTP.</para>
            <para>Netty HTTP uses the same properties as Netty TCP but adds the following additional
                properties:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>http-enabled</literal>. This is now no longer needed as of version 2.4. With single
                        port support HornetQ will now automatically detect if http is being used and configure itself.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>http-client-idle-time</literal>. How long a client can be idle
                        before sending an empty http request to keep the connection alive</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>http-client-idle-scan-period</literal>. How often, in
                        milliseconds, to scan for idle clients</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>http-response-time</literal>. How long the server can wait before
                        sending an empty http response to keep the connection alive</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>http-server-scan-period</literal>. How often, in milliseconds, to
                        scan for clients needing responses</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>http-requires-session-id</literal>. If true the client will wait
                        after the first call to receive a session id. Used the http connector is
                        connecting to servlet acceptor (not recommended) </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Configuring Netty Servlet</title>
            <para>As of 2.4 HornetQ Servlet support will be provided via Undertow in Wildfly</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
