<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<!-- Copyright © 2009 Red Hat, Inc. and others.                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- The text of and illustrations in this document are licensed by Red Hat under  -->
<!-- a Creative Commons Attribution–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license ("CC-BY-SA"). -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- An explanation of CC-BY-SA is available at                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!--            http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/.                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- In accordance with CC-BY-SA, if you distribute this document or an adaptation -->
<!-- of it, you must provide the URL for the original version.                     -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- Red Hat, as the licensor of this document, waives the right to enforce,       -->
<!-- and agrees not to assert, Section 4d of CC-BY-SA to the fullest extent        -->
<!-- permitted by applicable law.                                                  -->
<!-- ============================================================================= -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "HornetQ_User_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="core-bridges">
    <title>Core Bridges</title>
    <para>The function of a bridge is to consume messages from a source queue, and forward them to a
        target address, typically on a different HornetQ server.</para>
    <para>The source and target servers do not have to be in the same cluster which makes bridging
        suitable for reliably sending messages from one cluster to another, for instance across a
        WAN, or internet and where the connection may be unreliable.</para>
    <para>The bridge has built in resilience to failure so if the target server connection is lost,
        e.g. due to network failure, the bridge will retry connecting to the target until it comes
        back online. When it comes back online it will resume operation as normal.</para>
    <para>In summary, bridges are a way to reliably connect two separate HornetQ servers together.
        With a core bridge both source and target servers must be HornetQ servers.</para>
    <para>Bridges can be configured to provide <emphasis>once and only once</emphasis> delivery
        guarantees even in the event of the failure of the source or the target server. They do this
        by using duplicate detection (described in <xref linkend="duplicate-detection"/>).</para>
    <note>
        <para>Although they have similar function, don't confuse core bridges with JMS
            bridges!</para>
        <para>Core bridges are for linking a HornetQ node with another HornetQ node and do not use
            the JMS API. A JMS Bridge is used for linking any two JMS 1.1 compliant JMS providers.
            So, a JMS Bridge could be used for bridging to or from different JMS compliant messaging
            system. It's always preferable to use a core bridge if you can. Core bridges use
            duplicate detection to provide <emphasis>once and only once</emphasis> guarantees. To
            provide the same guarantee using a JMS bridge you would have to use XA which has a
            higher overhead and is more complex to configure.</para>
    </note>
    <section>
        <title>Configuring Bridges</title>
        <para>Bridges are configured in <literal>hornetq-configuration.xml</literal>. Let's kick off
            with an example (this is actually from the bridge example):</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;bridge name="my-bridge">
   &lt;queue-name>jms.queue.sausage-factory&lt;/queue-name>
   &lt;forwarding-address>jms.queue.mincing-machine&lt;/forwarding-address>
   &lt;filter-string="name='aardvark'"/>
   &lt;transformer-class-name>
      org.apache.activemq6.jms.example.HatColourChangeTransformer
   &lt;/transformer-class-name>
   &lt;retry-interval>1000&lt;/retry-interval>
   &lt;ha>true&lt;/ha>
   &lt;retry-interval-multiplier>1.0&lt;/retry-interval-multiplier>
   &lt;initial-connect-attempts>-1&lt;/initial-connect-attempts>
   &lt;reconnect-attempts>-1&lt;/reconnect-attempts>
   &lt;failover-on-server-shutdown>false&lt;/failover-on-server-shutdown>
   &lt;use-duplicate-detection>true&lt;/use-duplicate-detection>
   &lt;confirmation-window-size>10000000&lt;/confirmation-window-size>
   &lt;user>foouser&lt;/user>
   &lt;password>foopassword&lt;/password>
   &lt;static-connectors>
      &lt;connector-ref>remote-connector&lt;/connector-ref>
   &lt;/static-connectors>
   &lt;!-- alternative to static-connectors
   &lt;discovery-group-ref discovery-group-name="bridge-discovery-group"/>
   -->
&lt;/bridge></programlisting>
        <para>In the above example we have shown all the parameters its possible to configure for a
            bridge. In practice you might use many of the defaults so it won't be necessary to
            specify them all explicitly.</para>
        <para>Let's take a look at all the parameters in turn:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>name</literal> attribute. All bridges must have a unique name in the
                    server.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>queue-name</literal>. This is the unique name of the local queue that
                    the bridge consumes from, it's a mandatory parameter.</para>
                <para>The queue must already exist by the time the bridge is instantiated at
                    start-up.</para>
                <note>
                    <para>If you're using JMS then normally the JMS configuration <literal
                            >hornetq-jms.xml</literal> is loaded after the core configuration file
                            <literal>hornetq-configuration.xml</literal> is loaded. If your bridge
                        is consuming from a JMS queue then you'll need to make sure the JMS queue is
                        also deployed as a core queue in the core configuration. Take a look at the
                        bridge example for an example of how this is done.</para>
                </note>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>forwarding-address</literal>. This is the address on the target
                    server that the message will be forwarded to. If a forwarding address is not
                    specified, then the original address of the message will be retained.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>filter-string</literal>. An optional filter string can be supplied.
                    If specified then only messages which match the filter expression specified in
                    the filter string will be forwarded. The filter string follows the HornetQ
                    filter expression syntax described in <xref linkend="filter-expressions"
                    />.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>transformer-class-name</literal>. An optional transformer-class-name
                    can be specified. This is the name of a user-defined class which implements the
                        <literal>org.apache.activemq6.core.server.cluster.Transformer</literal>
                    interface.</para>
                <para>If this is specified then the transformer's <literal>transform()</literal>
                    method will be invoked with the message before it is forwarded. This gives you
                    the opportunity to transform the message's header or body before forwarding
                    it.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>ha</literal>. This optional parameter determines whether or not this
                   bridge should support high availability. True means it will connect to any available
                   server in a cluster and support failover. The default value is <literal
                        >false</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>retry-interval</literal>. This optional parameter determines the
                    period in milliseconds between subsequent reconnection attempts, if the
                    connection to the target server has failed. The default value is <literal
                        >2000</literal>milliseconds.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>retry-interval-multiplier</literal>. This optional parameter
                    determines determines a multiplier to apply to the time since the last retry to
                    compute the time to the next retry.</para>
                <para>This allows you to implement an <emphasis>exponential backoff</emphasis>
                    between retry attempts.</para>
                <para>Let's take an example:</para>
                <para>If we set <literal>retry-interval</literal>to <literal>1000</literal> ms and
                    we set <literal>retry-interval-multiplier</literal> to <literal>2.0</literal>,
                    then, if the first reconnect attempt fails, we will wait <literal>1000</literal>
                    ms then <literal>2000</literal> ms then <literal>4000</literal> ms between
                    subsequent reconnection attempts.</para>
                <para>The default value is <literal>1.0</literal> meaning each reconnect attempt is
                    spaced at equal intervals.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>initial-connect-attempts</literal>. This optional parameter determines the
                    total number of initial connect attempts the bridge will make before giving up and
                    shutting down. A value of <literal>-1</literal> signifies an unlimited number of
                    attempts. The default value is <literal>-1</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>reconnect-attempts</literal>. This optional parameter determines the
                    total number of reconnect attempts the bridge will make before giving up and
                    shutting down. A value of <literal>-1</literal> signifies an unlimited number of
                    attempts. The default value is <literal>-1</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>failover-on-server-shutdown</literal>. This optional parameter
                    determines whether the bridge will attempt to failover onto a backup server (if
                    specified) when the target server is cleanly shutdown rather than
                    crashed.</para>
                <para>The bridge connector can specify both a live and a backup server, if it
                    specifies a backup server and this parameter is set to <literal>true</literal>
                    then if the target server is <emphasis>cleanly</emphasis> shutdown the bridge
                    connection will attempt to failover onto its backup. If the bridge connector has
                    no backup server configured then this parameter has no effect. </para>
                <para>Sometimes you want a bridge configured with a live and a backup target server,
                    but you don't want to failover to the backup if the live server is simply taken
                    down temporarily for maintenance, this is when this parameter comes in
                    handy.</para>
                <para>The default value for this parameter is <literal>false</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>use-duplicate-detection</literal>. This optional parameter determines
                    whether the bridge will automatically insert a duplicate id property into each
                    message that it forwards.</para>
                <para>Doing so, allows the target server to perform duplicate detection on messages
                    it receives from the source server. If the connection fails or server crashes,
                    then, when the bridge resumes it will resend unacknowledged messages. This might
                    result in duplicate messages being sent to the target server. By enabling
                    duplicate detection allows these duplicates to be screened out and
                    ignored.</para>
                <para>This allows the bridge to provide a <emphasis>once and only once</emphasis>
                    delivery guarantee without using heavyweight methods such as XA (see <xref
                        linkend="duplicate-detection"/> for more information).</para>
                <para>The default value for this parameter is <literal>true</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>confirmation-window-size</literal>. This optional parameter
                    determines the <literal>confirmation-window-size</literal> to use for the
                    connection used to forward messages to the target node. This attribute is
                    described in section <xref linkend="client-reconnection"/></para>

                <warning><para>When using the bridge to forward messages to an address which uses
                    the <literal>BLOCK</literal> <literal>address-full-policy</literal> from a
                    queue which has a <literal>max-size-bytes</literal> set it's important that
                    <literal>confirmation-window-size</literal> is less than or equal to
                    <literal>max-size-bytes</literal> to prevent the flow of messages from
                    ceasing.</para>
                </warning>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>user</literal>. This optional parameter determines the user name to
                    use when creating the bridge connection to the remote server. If it is not
                    specified the default cluster user specified by <literal>cluster-user</literal>
                    in <literal>hornetq-configuration.xml</literal> will be used. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>password</literal>. This optional parameter determines the password
                    to use when creating the bridge connection to the remote server. If it is not
                    specified the default cluster password specified by <literal
                            >cluster-password</literal> in <literal>hornetq-configuration.xml</literal>
                    will be used. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>static-connectors</literal> or <literal>discovery-group-ref</literal>.
                    Pick either of these options to connect the bridge to the target server.
                </para>
                <para> The <literal>static-connectors</literal> is a list of <literal>connector-ref</literal>
                    elements pointing to <literal>connector</literal> elements defined elsewhere.
                    A <emphasis>connector</emphasis> encapsulates knowledge of what transport to
                    use (TCP, SSL, HTTP etc) as well as the server connection parameters (host, port
                    etc). For more information about what connectors are and how to configure them,
                    please see <xref linkend="configuring-transports"/>.
                </para>
                <para>The <literal>discovery-group-ref</literal> element has one attribute -
                    <literal>discovery-group-name</literal>.  This attribute points to a
                    <literal>discovery-group</literal> defined elsewhere. For more information about
                    what discovery-groups are and how to configure them, please see
                    <xref linkend="clusters.discovery-groups"/>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
