<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<!-- Copyright © 2009 Red Hat, Inc. and others.                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- The text of and illustrations in this document are licensed by Red Hat under  -->
<!-- a Creative Commons Attribution–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license ("CC-BY-SA"). -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- An explanation of CC-BY-SA is available at                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!--            http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/.                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- In accordance with CC-BY-SA, if you distribute this document or an adaptation -->
<!-- of it, you must provide the URL for the original version.                     -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- Red Hat, as the licensor of this document, waives the right to enforce,       -->
<!-- and agrees not to assert, Section 4d of CC-BY-SA to the fullest extent        -->
<!-- permitted by applicable law.                                                  -->
<!-- ============================================================================= -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ActiveMQ_User_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<chapter id="duplicate-detection">
    <title>Duplicate Message Detection</title>
    <para>ActiveMQ includes powerful automatic duplicate message detection, filtering out
        duplicate messages without you having to code your own fiddly duplicate detection logic at
        the application level. This chapter will explain what duplicate detection is, how ActiveMQ
        uses it and how and where to configure it.</para>
    <para>When sending messages from a client to a server, or indeed from a server to another
        server, if the target server or connection fails sometime after sending the message, but
        before the sender receives a response that the send (or commit) was processed successfully
        then the sender cannot know for sure if the message was sent successfully to the
        address.</para>
    <para>If the target server or connection failed after the send was received and processed but
        before the response was sent back then the message will have been sent to the address
        successfully, but if the target server or connection failed before the send was received and
        finished processing then it will not have been sent to the address successfully. From the
        senders point of view it's not possible to distinguish these two cases.</para>
    <para>When the server recovers this leaves the client in a difficult situation. It knows the
        target server failed, but it does not know if the last message reached its destination ok.
        If it decides to resend the last message, then that could result in a duplicate message
        being sent to the address. If each message was an order or a trade then this could result in
        the order being fulfilled twice or the trade being double booked. This is clearly not a
        desirable situation.</para>
    <para>Sending the message(s) in a transaction does not help out either. If the server or
        connection fails while the transaction commit is being processed it is also indeterminate
        whether the transaction was successfully committed or not!</para>
    <para>To solve these issues ActiveMQ provides automatic duplicate messages detection for
        messages sent to addresses.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Using Duplicate Detection for Message Sending</title>
        <para>Enabling duplicate message detection for sent messages is simple: you just need to set
            a special property on the message to a unique value. You can create the value however
            you like, as long as it is unique. When the target server receives the message it will
            check if that property is set, if it is, then it will check in its in memory cache if it
            has already received a message with that value of the header. If it has received a
            message with the same value before then it will ignore the message.</para>
        <note>
            <para>Using duplicate detection to move messages between nodes can give you the same
                    <emphasis>once and only once</emphasis> delivery guarantees as if you were using
                an XA transaction to consume messages from source and send them to the target, but
                with less overhead and much easier configuration than using XA.</para>
        </note>
        <para>If you're sending messages in a transaction then you don't have to set the property
            for <emphasis>every</emphasis> message you send in that transaction, you only need to
            set it once in the transaction. If the server detects a duplicate message for any
            message in the transaction, then it will ignore the entire transaction.</para>
        <para>The name of the property that you set is given by the value of <literal
                >org.apache.activemq.api.core.Message.HDR_DUPLICATE_DETECTION_ID</literal>, which
            is <literal>_HQ_DUPL_ID</literal></para>
        <para>The value of the property can be of type <literal>byte[]</literal> or <literal
                >SimpleString</literal> if you're using the core API. If you're using JMS it must be
            a <literal>String</literal>, and its value should be unique. An easy way of generating
            a unique id is by generating a UUID.</para>
        <para>Here's an example of setting the property using the core API:</para>
        <programlisting>
...     

ClientMessage message = session.createMessage(true);

SimpleString myUniqueID = "This is my unique id";   // Could use a UUID for this

message.setStringProperty(HDR_DUPLICATE_DETECTION_ID, myUniqueID);

...</programlisting>
        <para>And here's an example using the JMS API:</para>
        <programlisting>
...     

Message jmsMessage = session.createMessage();

String myUniqueID = "This is my unique id";   // Could use a UUID for this

message.setStringProperty(HDR_DUPLICATE_DETECTION_ID.toString(), myUniqueID);

...</programlisting>
    </section>
    <section id="duplicate.id.cache">
        <title>Configuring the Duplicate ID Cache</title>
        <para>The server maintains caches of received values of the <literal
                >org.apache.activemq.core.message.impl.HDR_DUPLICATE_DETECTION_ID</literal> property
            sent to each address. Each address has its own distinct cache.</para>
        <para>The cache is a circular fixed size cache. If the cache has a maximum size of <literal
                >n</literal> elements, then the <literal>n + 1</literal>th id stored will overwrite
            the <literal>0</literal>th element in the cache.</para>
        <para>The maximum size of the cache is configured by the parameter <literal
                >id-cache-size</literal> in <literal>activemq-configuration.xml</literal>, the default
            value is <literal>2000</literal> elements.</para>
        <para>The caches can also be configured to persist to disk or not. This is configured by the
            parameter <literal>persist-id-cache</literal>, also in <literal
                >activemq-configuration.xml</literal>. If this is set to <literal>true</literal> then
            each id will be persisted to permanent storage as they are received. The default value
            for this parameter is <literal>true</literal>.</para>
        <note>
            <para>When choosing a size of the duplicate id cache be sure to set it to a larger
                enough size so if you resend messages all the previously sent ones are in the cache
                not having been overwritten.</para>
        </note>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Duplicate Detection and Bridges</title>
        <para>Core bridges can be configured to automatically add a unique duplicate id value (if there
            isn't already one in the message) before forwarding the message to it's target. This
            ensures that if the target server crashes or the connection is interrupted and the
            bridge resends the message, then if it has already been received by the target server,
            it will be ignored.</para>
        <para>To configure a core bridge to add the duplicate id header, simply set the <parameter
                >use-duplicate-detection</parameter> to <literal>true</literal> when configuring a
            bridge in <literal>activemq-configuration.xml</literal>.</para>
        <para>The default value for this parameter is <literal>true</literal>.</para>
        <para>For more information on core bridges and how to configure them, please see 
                <xref linkend="core-bridges" />.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Duplicate Detection and Cluster Connections</title>
        <para>Cluster connections internally use core bridges to move messages reliable between
            nodes of the cluster. Consequently they can also be configured to insert the duplicate
            id header for each message they move using their internal bridges.</para>
        <para>To configure a cluster connection to add the duplicate id header, simply set the
                <parameter>use-duplicate-detection</parameter> to <literal>true</literal> when
            configuring a cluster connection in <literal>activemq-configuration.xml</literal>.</para>
        <para>The default value for this parameter is <literal>true</literal>.</para>
        <para>For more information on cluster connections and how to configure them, please see <xref
                linkend="clusters"/>.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
