<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<!-- Copyright © 2009 Red Hat, Inc. and others.                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- The text of and illustrations in this document are licensed by Red Hat under  -->
<!-- a Creative Commons Attribution–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license ("CC-BY-SA"). -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- An explanation of CC-BY-SA is available at                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!--            http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/.                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- In accordance with CC-BY-SA, if you distribute this document or an adaptation -->
<!-- of it, you must provide the URL for the original version.                     -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- Red Hat, as the licensor of this document, waives the right to enforce,       -->
<!-- and agrees not to assert, Section 4d of CC-BY-SA to the fullest extent        -->
<!-- permitted by applicable law.                                                  -->
<!-- ============================================================================= -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "HornetQ_User_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="ha">
    <title>High Availability and Failover</title>

    <para>We define high availability as the <emphasis>ability for the system to continue
       functioning after failure of one or more of the servers</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>A part of high availability is <emphasis>failover</emphasis> which we define as the
       <emphasis>ability for client connections to migrate from one server to another in event of
          server failure so client applications can continue to operate</emphasis>.</para>

    <section>
        <title>Live - Backup Groups</title>

        <para>HornetQ allows servers to be linked together as <emphasis>live - backup</emphasis>
           groups where each live server can have 1 or more backup servers. A backup server is owned by
           only one live server.  Backup servers are not operational until failover occurs, however 1
           chosen backup, which will be in passive mode, announces its status and waits to take over
           the live servers work</para>

        <para>Before failover, only the live server is serving the HornetQ clients while the backup
           servers remain passive or awaiting to become a backup server. When a live server crashes or
           is brought down in the correct mode, the backup server currently in passive mode will become
           live and another backup server will become passive. If a live server restarts after a
           failover then it will have priority and be the next server to become live when the current
           live server goes down, if the current live server is configured to allow automatic failback
           then it will detect the live server coming back up and automatically stop.</para>

        <section id="ha.mode">
            <title>HA modes</title>
            <para>HornetQ supports two different strategies for backing up a server <emphasis>shared
               store</emphasis> and <emphasis>replication</emphasis>.</para>
            <note>
                <para>Only persistent message data will survive failover. Any non persistent message
                   data will not be available after failover.</para>
            </note>
        </section>

        <section id="ha.mode.replicated">
            <title>Data Replication</title>
            <para>Support for network-based data replication was added in version 2.3.</para>
            <para>When using replication, the live and the backup servers do not share the same
               data directories, all data synchronization is done over the network. Therefore all (persistent)
               data received by the live server will be duplicated to the backup.</para>
            <graphic fileref="images/ha-replicated-store.png" align="center"/>
            <para>Notice that upon start-up the backup server will first need to synchronize all
               existing data from the live server before becoming capable of replacing the live
               server should it fail. So unlike when using shared storage, a replicating backup will
               not be a fully operational backup right after start-up, but only after it finishes
               synchronizing the data with its live server. The time it will take for this to happen
               will depend on the amount of data to be synchronized and the connection speed.</para>

            <note>
                <para>Synchronization occurs in parallel with current network traffic so this won't cause any
                  blocking on current clients.</para>
            </note>
            <para>Replication will create a copy of the data at the backup. One issue to be aware
               of is: in case of a successful fail-over, the backup's data will be newer than
               the one at the live's storage. If you configure your live server to perform a
               <xref linkend="ha.allow-fail-back">'fail-back'</xref> when restarted, it will synchronize
               its data with the backup's. If both servers are shutdown, the administrator will have
               to determine which one has the lastest data.</para>

            <para>The replicating live and backup pair must be part of a cluster.  The Cluster
               Connection also defines how backup servers will find the remote live servers to pair
               with.  Refer to <xref linkend="clusters"/> for details on how this is done, and how
               to configure a cluster connection. Notice that:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Both live and backup servers must be part of the same cluster.  Notice
                       that even a simple live/backup replicating pair will require a cluster configuration.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Their cluster user and password must match.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>Within a cluster, there are two ways that a backup server will locate a live server to replicate
               from, these are:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>specifying a node group</literal>. You can specify a group of live servers that a backup
                       server can connect to. This is done by configuring <literal>backup-group-name</literal> in the main
                       <literal>hornetq-configuration.xml</literal>. A Backup server will only connect to a live server that
                       shares the same node group name</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                   <para><literal>connecting to any live</literal>. Simply put not configuring <literal>backup-group-name</literal>
                      will allow a backup server to connect to any live server</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <note>
                <para>A <literal>backup-group-name</literal> example: suppose you have 5 live servers and 6 backup
                   servers:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><literal>live1</literal>, <literal>live2</literal>, <literal>live3</literal>: with
                           <literal>backup-group-name=fish</literal></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                       <para><literal>live4</literal>, <literal>live5</literal>: with <literal>backup-group-name=bird</literal></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                       <para><literal>backup1</literal>, <literal>backup2</literal>, <literal>backup3</literal>,
                          <literal>backup4</literal>: with <literal>backup-group-name=fish</literal></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                       <para><literal>backup5</literal>, <literal>backup6</literal>: with
                          <literal>backup-group-name=bird</literal></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>After joining the cluster the backups with <literal>backup-group-name=fish</literal> will
                   search for live servers with <literal>backup-group-name=fish</literal> to pair with. Since there
                   is one backup too many, the <literal>fish</literal> will remain with one spare backup.</para>
                <para>The 2 backups with <literal>backup-group-name=bird</literal> (<literal>backup5</literal> and
                   <literal>backup6</literal>) will pair with live servers <literal>live4</literal> and
                   <literal>live5</literal>.</para>
            </note>
            <para>The backup will search for any live server that it is configured to connect to. It then tries to
               replicate with each live server in turn until it finds a live server that has no current backup
               configured. If no live server is available it will wait until the cluster topology changes and
               repeats the process.</para>
            <note>
               <para>This is an important distinction from a shared-store backup, as in that case if
                  the backup starts and does not find its live server, the server will just activate
                  and start to serve client requests. In the replication case, the backup just keeps
                  waiting for a live server to pair with. Notice that in replication the backup server
                  does not know whether any data it might have is up to date, so it really cannot
                  decide to activate automatically. To activate a replicating backup server using the data
                  it has, the administrator must change its configuration to make a live server of it,
                  that change <literal>backup=true</literal> to <literal>backup=false</literal>.</para>
            </note>

            <para>Much like in the shared-store case, when the live server stops or crashes,
               its replicating backup will become active and take over its duties. Specifically,
               the backup will become active when it loses connection to its live server. This can
               be problematic because this can also happen because of a temporary network
               problem. In order to address this issue, the backup will try to determine whether it
               still can connect to the other servers in the cluster. If it can connect to more
               than half the servers, it will become active, if more than half the servers also
               disappeared with the live, the backup will wait and try reconnecting with the live.
               This avoids a split brain situation.</para>

            <section>
                <title>Configuration</title>

                <para>To configure the live and backup servers to be a replicating pair, configure
                   both servers' <literal>hornetq-configuration.xml</literal> to have:</para>

                <programlisting>
&lt;!-- FOR BOTH LIVE AND BACKUP SERVERS' -->
&lt;shared-store>false&lt;/shared-store>
.
.
&lt;cluster-connections>
   &lt;cluster-connection name="my-cluster">
      ...
   &lt;/cluster-connection>
&lt;/cluster-connections>
                </programlisting>

                <para>The backup server must also be configured as a backup.</para>

                <programlisting>
&lt;backup>true&lt;/backup>
</programlisting>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section id="ha.mode.shared">
            <title>Shared Store</title>
            <para>When using a shared store, both live and backup servers share the
               <emphasis>same</emphasis> entire data directory using a shared file system.
               This means the paging directory, journal directory, large messages and binding
               journal.</para>
            <para>When failover occurs and a backup server takes over, it will load the
               persistent storage from the shared file system and clients can connect to
               it.</para>
            <para>This style of high availability differs from data replication in that it
               requires a shared file system which is accessible by both the live and backup
               nodes. Typically this will be some kind of high performance Storage Area Network
               (SAN). We do not recommend you use Network Attached Storage (NAS), e.g. NFS
               mounts to store any shared journal (NFS is slow).</para>
            <para>The advantage of shared-store high availability is that no replication occurs
               between the live and backup nodes, this means it does not suffer any performance
               penalties due to the overhead of replication during normal operation.</para>
            <para>The disadvantage of shared store replication is that it requires a shared file
               system, and when the backup server activates it needs to load the journal from
               the shared store which can take some time depending on the amount of data in the
               store.</para>
            <para>If you require the highest performance during normal operation, have access to
               a fast SAN, and can live with a slightly slower failover (depending on amount of
               data), we recommend shared store high availability</para>
            <graphic fileref="images/ha-shared-store.png" align="center"/>

            <section id="ha/mode.shared.configuration">
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>To configure the live and backup servers to share their store, configure
                   all <literal>hornetq-configuration.xml</literal>:</para>
                <programlisting>
&lt;shared-store>true&lt;/shared-store>
                </programlisting>
                <para>Additionally, each backup server must be flagged explicitly as a backup:</para>
                <programlisting>
&lt;backup>true&lt;/backup></programlisting>
                <para>In order for live - backup groups to operate properly with a shared store,
                   both servers must have configured the location of journal directory to point
                   to the <emphasis>same shared location</emphasis> (as explained in
                   <xref linkend="configuring.message.journal"/>)</para>
                <note>
                    <para>todo write something about GFS</para>
                </note>
                <para>Also each node, live and backups, will need to have a cluster connection defined even if not
                   part of a cluster. The Cluster Connection info defines how backup servers announce there presence
                   to its live server or any other nodes in the cluster. Refer to <xref linkend="clusters"/> for details
                   on how this is done.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section id="ha.allow-fail-back">
            <title>Failing Back to live Server</title>
            <para>After a live server has failed and a backup taken has taken over its duties, you may want to
               restart the live server and have clients fail back.</para>
            <para>In case of "shared disk", simply restart the original live
               server and kill the new live server. You can do this by killing the process itself or just waiting for the server to crash naturally.</para>
            <para>In case of a replicating live server that has been replaced by a remote backup you will need to also set <link linkend="hq.check-for-live-server">check-for-live-server</link>. This option is necessary because a starting server cannot know whether there is a (remote) server running in its place, so with this option set, the server will check the cluster for another server using its node-ID and if it finds one it will try initiate a fail-back. This option only applies to live servers that are restarting, it is ignored by backup servers.</para>
            <para>It is also possible to cause failover to occur on normal server shutdown, to enable
               this set the following property to true in the <literal>hornetq-configuration.xml</literal>
               configuration file like so:</para>
            <programlisting>
&lt;failover-on-shutdown>true&lt;/failover-on-shutdown></programlisting>
            <para>By default this is set to false, if by some chance you have set this to false but still
               want to stop the server normally and cause failover then you can do this by using the management
               API as explained at <xref linkend="management.core.server"/></para>
            <para>You can also force the running live server to shutdown when the old live server comes back up allowing
               the original live server to take over automatically by setting the following property in the
               <literal>hornetq-configuration.xml</literal> configuration file as follows:</para>
            <programlisting>
&lt;allow-failback>true&lt;/allow-failback></programlisting>
            <para id="hq.check-for-live-server">In replication HA mode you need to set an extra property <literal>check-for-live-server</literal>
               to <literal>true</literal>. If set to true, during start-up a live server will first search the cluster for another server using its nodeID. If it finds one, it will contact this server and try to "fail-back". Since this is a remote replication scenario, the "starting live" will have to synchronize its data with the server running with its ID, once they are in sync, it will request the other server (which it assumes it is a back that has assumed its duties) to shutdown for it to take over. This is necessary because otherwise the live server has no means to know whether there was a fail-over or not, and if there was if the server that took its duties is still running or not. To configure this option at your <literal>hornetq-configuration.xml</literal> configuration file as follows:</para>
            <programlisting>
&lt;check-for-live-server>true&lt;/check-for-live-server></programlisting>
        </section>
        <section id="ha.colocated">
            <title>Colocated Backup Servers</title>
            <para>It is also possible when running standalone to colocate backup servers in the same
                JVM as another live server.The colocated backup will become a backup for another live
                server in the cluster but not the one it shares the vm with. To configure a colocated
                backup server simply add the following to the <literal>hornetq-configuration.xml</literal> file</para>
            <programlisting>
&lt;backup-servers>
    &lt;backup-server name="backup2" inherit-configuration="true" port-offset="1000">
        &lt;configuration>
            &lt;bindings-directory>target/server1/data/messaging/bindings&lt;/bindings-directory>
            &lt;journal-directory>target/server1/data/messaging/journal&lt;/journal-directory>
            &lt;large-messages-directory>target/server1/data/messaging/largemessages&lt;/large-messages-directory>
            &lt;paging-directory>target/server1/data/messaging/paging&lt;/paging-directory>
        &lt;/configuration>
    &lt;/backup-server>
&lt;/backup-servers>
            </programlisting>
            <para> you will notice 3 attributes on the <literal>backup-server</literal>, <literal>name</literal>
                which is a unique name used to identify the backup server, <literal>inherit-configuration</literal>
            which if set to true means the server will inherit the configuration of its parent server
            and <literal>port-offset</literal> which is what the port for any netty connectors or
            acceptors will be increased by if the configuration is inherited.</para>
            <para>it is also possible to configure the backup server in the normal way, in this example you will
            notice we have changed the journal directories.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section id="failover">
        <title>Failover Modes</title>
        <para>HornetQ defines two types of client failover:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Automatic client failover</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Application-level client failover</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>HornetQ also provides 100% transparent automatic reattachment of connections to the
            same server (e.g. in case of transient network problems). This is similar to failover,
            except it is reconnecting to the same server and is discussed in
            <xref linkend="client-reconnection"/></para>
        <para>During failover, if the client has consumers on any non persistent or temporary
            queues, those queues will be automatically recreated during failover on the backup node,
            since the backup node will not have any knowledge of non persistent queues.</para>
        <section id="ha.automatic.failover">
            <title>Automatic Client Failover</title>
            <para>HornetQ clients can be configured to receive knowledge of all live and backup servers, so
                that in event of connection failure at the client - live server connection, the
                client will detect this and reconnect to the backup server. The backup server will
                then automatically recreate any sessions and consumers that existed on each
                connection before failover, thus saving the user from having to hand-code manual
                reconnection logic.</para>
            <para>HornetQ clients detect connection failure when it has not received packets from
                the server within the time given by <literal>client-failure-check-period</literal>
                as explained in section <xref linkend="connection-ttl"/>. If the client does not
                receive data in good time, it will assume the connection has failed and attempt
                failover. Also if the socket is closed by the OS, usually if the server process is
                killed rather than the machine itself crashing, then the client will failover straight away.
                </para>
            <para>HornetQ clients can be configured to discover the list of live-backup server groups in a
                number of different ways. They can be configured explicitly or probably the most
                common way of doing this is to use <emphasis>server discovery</emphasis> for the
                client to automatically discover the list. For full details on how to configure
                server discovery, please see <xref linkend="clusters"/>.
                Alternatively, the clients can explicitly connect to a specific server and download
                the current servers and backups see <xref linkend="clusters"/>.</para>
            <para>To enable automatic client failover, the client must be configured to allow
                non-zero reconnection attempts (as explained in <xref linkend="client-reconnection"
                />).</para>
            <para>By default failover will only occur after at least one connection has been made to
                the live server. In other words, by default, failover will not occur if the client
                fails to make an initial connection to the live server - in this case it will simply
                retry connecting to the live server according to the reconnect-attempts property and
                fail after this number of attempts.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Failing over on the Initial Connection</title>
                <para>
                    Since the client does not learn about the full topology until after the first
                    connection is made there is a window where it does not know about the backup. If a failure happens at
                    this point the client can only try reconnecting to the original live server. To configure
                    how many attempts the client will make you can set the property <literal>initialConnectAttempts</literal>
                    on the <literal>ClientSessionFactoryImpl</literal> or <literal >HornetQConnectionFactory</literal> or
                    <literal>initial-connect-attempts</literal> in xml. The default for this is <literal>0</literal>, that
                    is try only once. Once the number of attempts has been made an exception will be thrown.
                </para>
            </section>
            <para>For examples of automatic failover with transacted and non-transacted JMS
                sessions, please see <xref linkend="examples.transaction-failover"/> and <xref
                    linkend="examples.non-transaction-failover"/>.</para>
            <section id="ha.automatic.failover.noteonreplication">
                <title>A Note on Server Replication</title>
                <para>HornetQ does not replicate full server state between live and backup servers.
                    When the new session is automatically recreated on the backup it won't have any
                    knowledge of messages already sent or acknowledged in that session. Any
                    in-flight sends or acknowledgements at the time of failover might also be
                    lost.</para>
                <para>By replicating full server state, theoretically we could provide a 100%
                    transparent seamless failover, which would avoid any lost messages or
                    acknowledgements, however this comes at a great cost: replicating the full
                    server state (including the queues, session, etc.). This would require
                    replication of the entire server state machine; every operation on the live
                    server would have to replicated on the replica server(s) in the exact same
                    global order to ensure a consistent replica state. This is extremely hard to do
                    in a performant and scalable way, especially when one considers that multiple
                    threads are changing the live server state concurrently.</para>
                <para>It is possible to provide full state machine replication using techniques such
                    as <emphasis role="italic">virtual synchrony</emphasis>, but this does not scale
                    well and effectively serializes all operations to a single thread, dramatically
                    reducing concurrency.</para>
                <para>Other techniques for multi-threaded active replication exist such as
                    replicating lock states or replicating thread scheduling but this is very hard
                    to achieve at a Java level.</para>
                <para>Consequently it has decided it was not worth massively reducing performance
                    and concurrency for the sake of 100% transparent failover. Even without 100%
                    transparent failover, it is simple to guarantee <emphasis role="italic">once and
                        only once</emphasis> delivery, even in the case of failure, by using a
                    combination of duplicate detection and retrying of transactions. However this is
                    not 100% transparent to the client code.</para>
            </section>
            <section id="ha.automatic.failover.blockingcalls">
                <title>Handling Blocking Calls During Failover</title>
                <para>If the client code is in a blocking call to the server, waiting for a response
                    to continue its execution, when failover occurs, the new session will not have
                    any knowledge of the call that was in progress. This call might otherwise hang
                    for ever, waiting for a response that will never come.</para>
                <para>To prevent this, HornetQ will unblock any blocking calls that were in progress
                    at the time of failover by making them throw a <literal
                        >javax.jms.JMSException</literal> (if using JMS), or a <literal
                        >HornetQException</literal> with error code <literal
                        >HornetQException.UNBLOCKED</literal>. It is up to the client code to catch
                    this exception and retry any operations if desired.</para>
                <para>If the method being unblocked is a call to commit(), or prepare(), then the
                    transaction will be automatically rolled back and HornetQ will throw a <literal
                        >javax.jms.TransactionRolledBackException</literal> (if using JMS), or a
                        <literal>HornetQException</literal> with error code <literal
                        >HornetQException.TRANSACTION_ROLLED_BACK</literal> if using the core
                    API.</para>
            </section>
            <section id="ha.automatic.failover.transactions">
                <title>Handling Failover With Transactions</title>
                <para>If the session is transactional and messages have already been sent or
                    acknowledged in the current transaction, then the server cannot be sure that
                    messages sent or acknowledgements have not been lost during the failover.</para>
                <para>Consequently the transaction will be marked as rollback-only, and any
                    subsequent attempt to commit it will throw a <literal
                        >javax.jms.TransactionRolledBackException</literal> (if using JMS), or a
                        <literal>HornetQException</literal> with error code <literal
                        >HornetQException.TRANSACTION_ROLLED_BACK</literal> if using the core
                    API.</para>
               <warning>
                  <title>2 phase commit</title>
                  <para>
                     The caveat to this rule is when XA is used either via JMS or through the core API.
                     If 2 phase commit is used and prepare has already been called then rolling back could
                     cause a <literal>HeuristicMixedException</literal>. Because of this the commit will throw
                     a <literal>XAException.XA_RETRY</literal> exception. This informs the Transaction Manager
                     that it should retry the commit at some later point in time, a side effect of this is
                     that any non persistent messages will be lost. To avoid this use persistent
                     messages when using XA. With acknowledgements this is not an issue since they are
                     flushed to the server before prepare gets called.
                  </para>
               </warning>
                <para>It is up to the user to catch the exception, and perform any client side local
                    rollback code as necessary. There is no need to manually rollback the session -
                    it is already rolled back. The user can then just retry the transactional
                    operations again on the same session.</para>
                <para>HornetQ ships with a fully functioning example demonstrating how to do this,
                    please see <xref linkend="examples.transaction-failover"/></para>
                <para>If failover occurs when a commit call is being executed, the server, as
                    previously described, will unblock the call to prevent a hang, since no response
                    will come back. In this case it is not easy for the client to determine whether
                    the transaction commit was actually processed on the live server before failure
                    occurred.</para>
               <note>
                  <para>
                     If XA is being used either via JMS or through the core API then an <literal>XAException.XA_RETRY</literal>
                     is thrown. This is to inform Transaction Managers that a retry should occur at some point. At
                     some later point in time the Transaction Manager will retry the commit. If the original
                     commit has not occurred then it will still exist and be committed, if it does not exist
                     then it is assumed to have been committed although the transaction manager may log a warning.
                  </para>
               </note>
                <para>To remedy this, the client can simply enable duplicate detection (<xref
                        linkend="duplicate-detection"/>) in the transaction, and retry the
                    transaction operations again after the call is unblocked. If the transaction had
                    indeed been committed on the live server successfully before failover, then when
                    the transaction is retried, duplicate detection will ensure that any durable
                    messages resent in the transaction will be ignored on the server to prevent them
                    getting sent more than once.</para>
                <note>
                    <para>By catching the rollback exceptions and retrying, catching unblocked calls
                        and enabling duplicate detection, once and only once delivery guarantees for
                        messages can be provided in the case of failure, guaranteeing 100% no loss
                        or duplication of messages.</para>
                </note>
            </section>
            <section id="ha.automatic.failover.nontransactional">
                <title>Handling Failover With Non Transactional Sessions</title>
                <para>If the session is non transactional, messages or acknowledgements can be lost
                    in the event of failover.</para>
                <para>If you wish to provide <emphasis role="italic">once and only once</emphasis>
                    delivery guarantees for non transacted sessions too, enabled duplicate
                    detection, and catch unblock exceptions as described in <xref
                        linkend="ha.automatic.failover.blockingcalls"/></para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Getting Notified of Connection Failure</title>
            <para>JMS provides a standard mechanism for getting notified asynchronously of
                connection failure: <literal>java.jms.ExceptionListener</literal>. Please consult
                the JMS javadoc or any good JMS tutorial for more information on how to use
                this.</para>
            <para>The HornetQ core API also provides a similar feature in the form of the class
                    <literal>org.hornet.core.client.SessionFailureListener</literal></para>
            <para>Any ExceptionListener or SessionFailureListener instance will always be called by
                HornetQ on event of connection failure, <emphasis role="bold"
                    >irrespective</emphasis> of whether the connection was successfully failed over,
                reconnected or reattached, however you can find out if reconnect or reattach has happened
            by either the <literal>failedOver</literal> flag passed in on the <literal>connectionFailed</literal>
               on <literal>SessionfailureListener</literal> or by inspecting the error code on the
               <literal>javax.jms.JMSException</literal> which will be one of the following:</para>
           <table frame="topbot" border="2">
              <title>JMSException error codes</title>
              <tgroup cols="2">
                 <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                 <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                 <thead>
                    <row>
                       <entry>error code</entry>
                       <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                 </thead>
                 <tbody>
                    <row>
                       <entry>FAILOVER</entry>
                       <entry>
                          Failover has occurred and we have successfully reattached or reconnected.
                       </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                       <entry>DISCONNECT</entry>
                       <entry>
                          No failover has occurred and we are disconnected.
                       </entry>
                    </row>
                 </tbody>
              </tgroup>
           </table>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Application-Level Failover</title>
            <para>In some cases you may not want automatic client failover, and prefer to handle any
                connection failure yourself, and code your own manually reconnection logic in your
                own failure handler. We define this as <emphasis>application-level</emphasis>
                failover, since the failover is handled at the user application level.</para>
            <para>To implement application-level failover, if you're using JMS then you need to set
                an <literal>ExceptionListener</literal> class on the JMS connection. The
                <literal>ExceptionListener</literal> will be called by HornetQ in the event that
                connection failure is detected. In your <literal>ExceptionListener</literal>, you
                would close your old JMS connections, potentially look up new connection factory
                instances from JNDI and creating new connections. In this case you may well be using
                <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/community/wiki/JBossHAJNDIImpl">HA-JNDI</ulink>
                to ensure that the new connection factory is looked up from a different server.</para>
            <para>For a working example of application-level failover, please see
                <xref linkend="application-level-failover"/>.</para>
            <para>If you are using the core API, then the procedure is very similar: you would set a
                    <literal>FailureListener</literal> on the core <literal>ClientSession</literal>
                instances.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
