<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<!-- Copyright © 2009 Red Hat, Inc. and others.                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- The text of and illustrations in this document are licensed by Red Hat under  -->
<!-- a Creative Commons Attribution–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license ("CC-BY-SA"). -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- An explanation of CC-BY-SA is available at                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!--            http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/.                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- In accordance with CC-BY-SA, if you distribute this document or an adaptation -->
<!-- of it, you must provide the URL for the original version.                     -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- Red Hat, as the licensor of this document, waives the right to enforce,       -->
<!-- and agrees not to assert, Section 4d of CC-BY-SA to the fullest extent        -->
<!-- permitted by applicable law.                                                  -->
<!-- ============================================================================= -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "HornetQ_User_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="interoperability">
    <title>Interoperability</title>
    <section id="stomp">
        <title>Stomp</title>
        <para><ulink url="http://stomp.github.com/">Stomp</ulink> is a text-orientated wire protocol that allows
            Stomp clients to communicate with Stomp Brokers. HornetQ now supports Stomp 1.0, 1.1 and 1.2.</para>
        <para>Stomp clients are available for
        several languages and platforms making it a good choice for interoperability.</para>
        <section id="stomp.native">
          <title>Native Stomp support</title>
          <para>HornetQ provides native support for Stomp. To be able to send and receive Stomp messages,
            you must configure a <literal>NettyAcceptor</literal> with a <literal>protocols</literal>
            parameter set to have <literal>stomp</literal>:</para>
<programlisting>
&lt;acceptor name="stomp-acceptor">
   &lt;factory-class>org.apache.activemq.core.remoting.impl.netty.NettyAcceptorFactory&lt;/factory-class>
   &lt;param key="protocols"  value="STOMP"/>
   &lt;param key="port"  value="61613"/>
&lt;/acceptor></programlisting>
          <para>With this configuration, HornetQ will accept Stomp connections on 
            the port <literal>61613</literal> (which is the default port of the Stomp brokers).</para>
          <para>See the <literal>stomp</literal> example which shows how to configure a HornetQ server with Stomp.</para>
          <section>
            <title>Limitations</title>
            <para>Message acknowledgements are not transactional. The ACK frame can not be part of a transaction
              (it will be ignored if its <literal>transaction</literal> header is set).</para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Stomp 1.1/1.2 Notes</title>
            <section>
				<title>Virtual Hosting</title>
                <para>HornetQ currently doesn't support virtual hosting, which means the 'host' header 
                in CONNECT fram will be ignored.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
				<title>Heart-beating</title>
                <para>HornetQ specifies a minimum value for both client and server heart-beat intervals. 
                The minimum interval for both client and server heartbeats is 500 milliseconds. That means if 
                a client sends a CONNECT frame with heartbeat values lower than 500, the server will defaults 
                the value to 500 milliseconds regardless the values of the 'heart-beat' header in the frame.</para>
            </section>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Mapping Stomp destinations to HornetQ addresses and queues</title>
          <para>Stomp clients deals with <emphasis>destinations</emphasis> when sending messages and subscribing.
            Destination names are simply strings which are mapped to some form of destination on the 
            server - how the server translates these is left to the server implementation.</para>
           <para>In HornetQ, these destinations are mapped to <emphasis>addresses</emphasis> and <emphasis>queues</emphasis>.
            When a Stomp client sends a message (using a <literal>SEND</literal> frame), the specified destination is mapped
            to an address.
            When a Stomp client subscribes (or unsubscribes) for a destination (using a <literal>SUBSCRIBE</literal>
            or <literal>UNSUBSCRIBE</literal> frame), the destination is mapped to a HornetQ queue.</para>
        </section>
      <section>
        <title>STOMP and connection-ttl</title>
        <para>Well behaved STOMP clients will always send a DISCONNECT frame before closing their connections. In this case the server
          will clear up any server side resources such as sessions and consumers synchronously. However if STOMP clients exit without
        sending a DISCONNECT frame or if they crash the server will have no way of knowing immediately whether the client is still alive
        or not. STOMP connections therefore default to a connection-ttl value of 1 minute (see chapter on <link linkend="connection-ttl"
          >connection-ttl</link> for more information. This value can be overridden using connection-ttl-override.
        </para>
        <para>If you need a specific connection-ttl for your stomp connections without affecting the connection-ttl-override setting, you
        can configure your stomp acceptor with the "connection-ttl" property, which is used to set the ttl for connections that are 
        created from that acceptor. For example:
        </para>
<programlisting>
&lt;acceptor name="stomp-acceptor">
   &lt;factory-class>org.apache.activemq.core.remoting.impl.netty.NettyAcceptorFactory&lt;/factory-class>
   &lt;param key="protocols"  value="STOMP"/>
   &lt;param key="port"  value="61613"/>
   &lt;param key="connection-ttl"  value="20000"/>
&lt;/acceptor></programlisting>
        <para>The above configuration will make sure that any stomp connection that is created from that acceptor will have its 
        connection-ttl set to 20 seconds.</para>

        <note><para>Please note that the STOMP protocol version 1.0 does not contain any heartbeat frame. It is therefore the user's 
        responsibility to make sure data is sent within connection-ttl or the server will assume the client is dead and clean up server 
        side resources. With <literal>Stomp 1.1</literal> users can use heart-beats to maintain the life cycle of stomp 
        connections.</para></note>
      </section>
      
        <section>
          <title>Stomp and JMS interoperability</title>
          <section>
            <title>Using JMS destinations</title>
            <para>As explained in <xref linkend="jms-core-mapping" />, JMS destinations are also mapped to HornetQ addresses and queues.
              If you want to use Stomp to send messages to JMS destinations, the Stomp destinations must follow the same convention:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>send or subscribe to a JMS <emphasis>Queue</emphasis> by prepending the queue name by <literal>jms.queue.</literal>.</para>
                <para>For example, to send a message to the <literal>orders</literal> JMS Queue, the Stomp client must send the frame:</para>
                <programlisting>
SEND
destination:jms.queue.orders

hello queue orders
^@</programlisting>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>send or subscribe to a JMS <emphasis>Topic</emphasis> by prepending the topic name by <literal>jms.topic.</literal>.</para>
                <para>For example to subscribe to the <literal>stocks</literal> JMS Topic, the Stomp client must send the frame:</para>
                <programlisting>
SUBSCRIBE
destination:jms.topic.stocks

^@</programlisting>
              </listitem>
             </itemizedlist>
           </section>

           <section>
             <title>Sending and consuming Stomp message from JMS or HornetQ Core API</title>
             <para>Stomp is mainly a text-orientated protocol. To make it simpler to interoperate with JMS and HornetQ Core API, 
               our Stomp implementation checks for presence of the <literal>content-length</literal> header to decide how to map a Stomp message
               to a JMS Message or a Core message.
             </para>
             <para>If the Stomp message does <emphasis>not</emphasis> have a <literal>content-length</literal> header, it will be mapped to a JMS <emphasis>TextMessage</emphasis>
               or a Core message with a <emphasis>single nullable SimpleString in the body buffer</emphasis>.</para>
             <para>Alternatively, if the Stomp message <emphasis>has</emphasis> a <literal>content-length</literal> header, 
               it will be mapped to a JMS <emphasis>BytesMessage</emphasis>
               or a Core message with a <emphasis>byte[] in the body buffer</emphasis>.</para>
             <para>The same logic applies when mapping a JMS message or a Core message to Stomp. A Stomp client can check the presence
                of the <literal>content-length</literal> header to determine the type of the message body (String or bytes).</para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Message IDs for Stomp messages</title>
            <para>When receiving Stomp messages via a JMS consumer or a QueueBrowser, the messages have
            no properties like JMSMessageID by default. However this may bring some inconvenience to 
            clients who wants an ID for their purpose. HornetQ Stomp provides a parameter to enable
            message ID on each incoming Stomp message. If you want each Stomp message to have a unique ID,
            just set the <literal>stomp-enable-message-id</literal> to true. For example:</para>
<programlisting>
&lt;acceptor name="stomp-acceptor">
   &lt;factory-class>org.apache.activemq.core.remoting.impl.netty.NettyAcceptorFactory&lt;/factory-class>
   &lt;param key="protocols" value="STOMP"/>
   &lt;param key="port" value="61613"/>
   &lt;param key="stomp-enable-message-id" value="true"/>
&lt;/acceptor></programlisting>
            <para>When the server starts with the above setting, each stomp message sent through this
            acceptor will have an extra property added. The property key is <literal>
            hq-message-id</literal> and the value is a String representation of a long type internal
            message id prefixed with "<literal>STOMP</literal>", like:
<programlisting>
hq-message-id : STOMP12345</programlisting>
            If <literal>stomp-enable-message-id</literal> is not specified in the configuration, default
            is <literal>false</literal>. </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Handling of Large Messages with Stomp</title>
            <para>Stomp clients may send very large bodys of frames which can exceed the size of HornetQ 
            server's internal buffer, causing unexpected errors. To prevent this situation from happening,
            HornetQ provides a stomp configuration attribute <literal>stomp-min-large-message-size</literal>. 
            This attribute can be configured inside a stomp acceptor, as a parameter. For example: </para>
<programlisting>
   &lt;acceptor name="stomp-acceptor">
   &lt;factory-class>org.apache.activemq.core.remoting.impl.netty.NettyAcceptorFactory&lt;/factory-class>
   &lt;param key="protocols" value="STOMP"/>
   &lt;param key="port" value="61613"/>
   &lt;param key="stomp-min-large-message-size" value="10240"/>
&lt;/acceptor></programlisting>
            <para>The type of this attribute is integer. When this attributed is configured, HornetQ server 
            will check the size of the body of each Stomp frame arrived from connections established with 
            this acceptor. If the size of the body is equal or greater than the value of 
            <literal>stomp-min-large-message</literal>, the message will be persisted as a large message.
            When a large message is delievered to a stomp consumer, the HorentQ server will automatically 
            handle the conversion from a large message to a normal message, before sending it to the client.</para>
            <para>If a large message is compressed, the server will uncompressed it before sending it to
            stomp clients. The default value of <literal>stomp-min-large-message-size</literal> is the same
            as the default value of <link linkend="large-messages.core.config">min-large-message-size</link>.</para>
          </section>
        </section>
        
        <section id="stomp.websockets">
         <title>Stomp Over Web Sockets</title>
         <para>HornetQ also support Stomp over <ulink url="http://dev.w3.org/html5/websockets/">Web Sockets</ulink>. Modern web browser which support Web Sockets can send and receive
            Stomp messages from HornetQ.</para>
         <para>To enable Stomp over Web Sockets, you must configure a <literal>NettyAcceptor</literal> with a <literal>protocol</literal>
            parameter set to <literal>stomp_ws</literal>:</para>
         <programlisting>
&lt;acceptor name="stomp-ws-acceptor">
   &lt;factory-class>org.apache.activemq.core.remoting.impl.netty.NettyAcceptorFactory&lt;/factory-class>
   &lt;param key="protocols" value="STOMP_WS"/>
   &lt;param key="port" value="61614"/>
&lt;/acceptor></programlisting>
         <para>With this configuration, HornetQ will accept Stomp connections over Web Sockets on 
            the port <literal>61614</literal> with the URL path <literal>/stomp</literal>.
            Web browser can then connect to <literal>ws://&lt;server>:61614/stomp</literal> using a Web Socket to send and receive Stomp
            messages.</para>
         <para>A companion JavaScript library to ease client-side development is available from 
            <ulink url="http://github.com/jmesnil/stomp-websocket">GitHub</ulink> (please see
            its <ulink url="http://jmesnil.net/stomp-websocket/doc/">documentation</ulink> for a complete description).</para>
         <para>The <literal>stomp-websockets</literal> example shows how to configure HornetQ server to have web browsers and Java
            applications exchanges messages on a JMS topic.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="stompconnect">
          <title>StompConnect</title>
          <para><ulink url="http://stomp.codehaus.org/StompConnect">StompConnect</ulink> is a server that
            can act as a Stomp broker and proxy the Stomp protocol to the standard JMS API.
            Consequently, using StompConnect it is possible to turn HornetQ into a Stomp Broker and
            use any of the available stomp clients. These include clients written in C, C++, c# and
            .net etc.</para>
          <para>To run StompConnect first start the HornetQ server and make sure that it is using
            JNDI.</para>
          <para>Stomp requires the file <literal>jndi.properties</literal> to be available on the
            classpath. This should look something like:</para>
          <programlisting>
java.naming.factory.initial=org.jnp.interfaces.NamingContextFactory
java.naming.provider.url=jnp://localhost:1099
java.naming.factory.url.pkgs=org.jboss.naming:org.jnp.interfaces</programlisting>
          <para>Make sure this file is in the classpath along with the StompConnect jar and the
            HornetQ jars and simply run <literal>java org.codehaus.stomp.jms.Main</literal>.</para>
        </section>
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>REST</title>
        <para>Please see <xref linkend="rest"/></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>AMQP</title>
        <para>HornetQ supports the <ulink url="https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=amqp">AMQP 1.0</ulink>
        specification. To enable AMQP you must configure a Netty Acceptor to receive AMQP clients, like so:</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;acceptor name="stomp-acceptor">
&lt;factory-class>org.apache.activemq.core.remoting.impl.netty.NettyAcceptorFactory&lt;/factory-class>
&lt;param key="protocols"  value="AMQP"/>
&lt;param key="port"  value="5672"/>
&lt;/acceptor>
        </programlisting>
        <para>HornetQ will then accept AMQP 1.0 clients on port 5672 which is the default AMQP port.</para>
        <para>There are 2 Stomp examples available see proton-j and proton-ruby which use the qpid Java and Ruby clients
        respectively</para>
        <section>
            <title>AMQP and security</title>
        <para>The HornetQ Server accepts AMQP SASL Authentication and will use this to map onto the underlying session created
            for the connection so you can use the normal HornetQ security configuration.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>AMQP Links</title>
        <para>An AMQP Link is a uni directional transport for messages between a source and a target, i.e. a client and the
        HornetQ Broker. A link will have an endpoint of which there are 2 kinds, a Sender and A Receiver. At the Broker a
            Sender will have its messages converted into a HornetQ Message and forwarded to its destination or target. A
        Receiver will map onto a HornetQ Server Consumer and convert HornetQ messages back into AMQP messages before being delivered.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>AMQP and destinations</title>
            <para>If an AMQP Link is dynamic then a temporary queue will be created and either the remote source or remote
                target address will be set to the name of the temporary queue. If the Link is not dynamic then the the address
                of the remote target or source will used for the queue. If this does not exist then an exception will be sent</para>
            <note><para>For the next version we will add a flag to aut create durable queue but for now you will have to add them via
                the configuration</para></note>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>AMQP and Coordinations - Handling Transactions</title>
            <para>An AMQP links target can also be a Coordinator, the Coordinator is used to handle transactions. If a
            coordinator is used the the underlying HormetQ Server session will be transacted and will be either rolled back
                or committed via the coordinator.</para>
            <note><para>AMQP allows the use of multiple transactions per session, <literal>amqp:multi-txns-per-ssn</literal>,
                however in this version HornetQ will only support single transactions per session</para></note>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>OpenWire</title>
        <para>HornetQ now supports the <ulink url="http://activemq.apache.org/openwire.html">OpenWire</ulink>
        protocol so that an ActiveMQ JMS client can talk directly to a HornetQ server. To enable OpenWire support
        you must configure a Netty Acceptor, like so:</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;acceptor name="openwire-acceptor">
&lt;factory-class>org.apache.activemq.core.remoting.impl.netty.NettyAcceptorFactory&lt;/factory-class>
&lt;param key="protocols"  value="OPENWIRE"/>
&lt;param key="port"  value="61616"/>
&lt;/acceptor>
        </programlisting>
        <para>The HornetQ server will then listens on port 61616 for incoming openwire commands. Please note the "protocols" is not mandatory here. 
        The openwire configuration conforms to HornetQ's "Single Port" feature. Please refer to 
        <link linkend="configuring-transports.single-port">Configuring Single Port</link> for details.</para>
        <para>Please refer to the openwire example for more coding details.</para>
        <para>Currently we support ActiveMQ clients that using standard JMS APIs. In the future we will get more supports
        for some advanced, ActiveMQ specific features into HornetQ.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
