<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more            -->
<!-- contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with          -->
<!-- this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.           -->
<!-- The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0       -->
<!-- (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with          -->
<!-- the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at                          -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!--     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0                                -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software           -->
<!-- distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,             -->
<!-- WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.      -->
<!-- See the License for the specific language governing permissions and           -->
<!-- limitations under the License.                                                -->
<!-- ============================================================================= -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
        <!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ActiveMQ_User_Manual.ent">
        %BOOK_ENTITIES;
        ]>
<chapter id="pre-acknowledge">
    <title>Extra Acknowledge Modes</title>
    <para>JMS specifies 3 acknowledgement modes:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><literal>AUTO_ACKNOWLEDGE</literal></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><literal>CLIENT_ACKNOWLEDGE</literal></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><literal>DUPS_OK_ACKNOWLEDGE</literal></para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>ActiveMQ supports two additional modes: <literal>PRE_ACKNOWLEDGE</literal> and <literal>INDIVIDUAL_ACKNOWLEDGE</literal></para>
    <para>In some cases you can afford
        to lose messages in event of failure, so it would make sense to acknowledge the message on the
        server <emphasis>before</emphasis> delivering it to the client.</para>
    <para>This extra mode is supported by ActiveMQ and will call it
        <emphasis>pre-acknowledge</emphasis> mode.</para>
    <para>The disadvantage of acknowledging on the server before delivery is that the message will be
        lost if the system crashes <emphasis>after</emphasis> acknowledging the message on the server
        but <emphasis>before</emphasis> it is delivered to the client. In that case, the message is
        lost and will not be recovered when the system restart.</para>
    <para>Depending on your messaging case, <literal>pre-acknowledgement</literal> mode can avoid
        extra network traffic and CPU at the cost of coping with message loss.</para>
    <para>An example of a use case for pre-acknowledgement is for stock price update messages. With
        these messages it might be reasonable to lose a message in event of crash, since the next
        price update message will arrive soon, overriding the previous price. </para>
    <note>
        <para>Please note, that if you use pre-acknowledge mode, then you will lose transactional
            semantics for messages being consumed, since clearly they are being acknowledged first on
            the server, not when you commit the transaction. This may be stating the obvious but we
            like to be clear on these things to avoid confusion!</para>
    </note>
    <section id="pre-acknowledge.configure">
        <title>Using PRE_ACKNOWLEDGE</title>
        <para>This can be configured in the <literal>activemq-jms.xml</literal> file on the <literal
                >connection factory</literal> like this:</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;connection-factory name="ConnectionFactory">
   &lt;connectors>
      &lt;connector-ref connector-name="netty-connector"/>
   &lt;/connectors>
   &lt;entries>
      &lt;entry name="ConnectionFactory"/>
   &lt;/entries>
   &lt;pre-acknowledge>true&lt;/pre-acknowledge>
&lt;/connection-factory></programlisting>
        <para>Alternatively, to use pre-acknowledgement mode using the JMS API, create a JMS Session
            with the <literal>ActiveMQSession.PRE_ACKNOWLEDGE</literal> constant.</para>
        <programlisting>
// messages will be acknowledge on the server *before* being delivered to the client
Session session = connection.createSession(false, ActiveMQJMSConstants.PRE_ACKNOWLEDGE);</programlisting>
        <para>Or you can set pre-acknowledge directly on the <literal
                >ActiveMQConnectionFactory</literal> instance using the setter method.</para>
        <para>To use pre-acknowledgement mode using the core API you can set it directly on the
            <literal>ClientSessionFactory</literal> instance using the setter method.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="individual-ack">
        <title>Individual Acknowledge</title>
        <para>A valid use-case for individual acknowledgement would be when you need to have your own scheduling and you don't know when your message processing will be finished. You should prefer having one consumer per thread worker
            but this is not possible in some circumstances depending on how complex is your processing. For that you can use the individual Acknowledgement. </para>
        <para>You basically setup Individual ACK by creating a session with the acknowledge mode with <literal>ActiveMQJMSConstants.INDIVIDUAL_ACKNOWLEDGE</literal>. Individual ACK inherits all the semantics from Client Acknowledge,
            with the exception the message is individually acked.</para>
        <note>
            <para>Please note, that to avoid confusion on MDB processing, Individual ACKNOWLEDGE is not supported through MDBs (or the inbound resource adapter). this is because you have to finish the process of your message inside the MDB.
            </para>
        </note>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Example</title>
        <para>See <xref linkend="examples.pre-acknowledge"/> for an example which shows how to use
            pre-acknowledgement mode with JMS.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
