<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more            -->
<!-- contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with          -->
<!-- this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.           -->
<!-- The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0       -->
<!-- (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with          -->
<!-- the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at                          -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!--     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0                                -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software           -->
<!-- distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,             -->
<!-- WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.      -->
<!-- See the License for the specific language governing permissions and           -->
<!-- limitations under the License.                                                -->
<!-- ============================================================================= -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ActiveMQ_User_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="queue-attributes">
    <title>Queue Attributes</title>
    <para>Queue attributes can be set in one of two ways. Either by configuring them using the
        configuration file or by using the core API. This chapter will explain how to configure each
        attribute and what effect the attribute has.</para>
    <section id="predefined.queues">
        <title>Predefined Queues</title>
        <para>Queues can be predefined via configuration at a core level or at a JMS level. Firstly
            let's look at a JMS level.</para>
        <para>The following shows a queue predefined in the <literal>activemq-jms.xml</literal>
            configuration file.</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;queue name="selectorQueue">
   &lt;entry name="/queue/selectorQueue"/>
   &lt;selector string="color='red'"/>
   &lt;durable>true&lt;/durable>
&lt;/queue></programlisting>
        <para>This name attribute of queue defines the name of the queue. When we do this at a jms
            level we follow a naming convention so the actual name of the core queue will be
                <literal>jms.queue.selectorQueue</literal>.</para>
        <para>The entry element configures the name that will be used to bind the queue to JNDI.
            This is a mandatory element and the queue can contain multiple of these to bind the same
            queue to different names.</para>
        <para>The selector element defines what JMS message selector the predefined queue will have.
            Only messages that match the selector will be added to the queue. This is an optional
            element with a default of null when omitted.</para>
        <para>The durable element specifies whether the queue will be persisted. This again is
            optional and defaults to true if omitted.</para>
        <para>Secondly a queue can be predefined at a core level in the <literal
                >activemq-configuration.xml</literal> file. The following is an example.</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;queues>
   &lt;queue name="jms.queue.selectorQueue">
      &lt;address>jms.queue.selectorQueue&lt;/address>
      &lt;filter string="color='red'"/>
      &lt;durable>true&lt;/durable>
    &lt;/queue>
&lt;/queues></programlisting>
        <para>This is very similar to the JMS configuration, with 3 real differences which
            are.</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The name attribute of queue is the actual name used for the queue with no
                    naming convention as in JMS.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The address element defines what address is used for routing messages.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>There is no entry element.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The filter uses the <emphasis>Core filter syntax</emphasis> (described in
                        <xref linkend="filter-expressions"/>), <emphasis>not</emphasis> the JMS
                    selector syntax.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Using the API</title>
        <para>Queues can also be created using the core API or the management API.</para>
        <para>For the core API, queues can be created via the <literal
                >org.apache.activemq.api.core.client.ClientSession</literal> interface. There are multiple
                <literal>createQueue</literal> methods that support setting all of the previously
            mentioned attributes. There is one extra attribute that can be set via this API which is
                <literal>temporary</literal>. setting this to true means that the queue will be
            deleted once the session is disconnected.</para>
        <para>Take a look at <xref linkend="management"/> for a description of the management API
            for creating queues.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="queue-attributes.address-settings">
        <title>Configuring Queues Via Address Settings</title>
        <para>There are some attributes that are defined against an address wildcard rather than a
            specific queue. Here an example of an <literal>address-setting</literal> entry that
            would be found in the <literal>activemq-configuration.xml</literal> file.</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;address-settings>
   &lt;address-setting match="jms.queue.exampleQueue">
      &lt;dead-letter-address>jms.queue.deadLetterQueue&lt;/dead-letter-address>
      &lt;max-delivery-attempts>3&lt;/max-delivery-attempts>
      &lt;redelivery-delay>5000&lt;/redelivery-delay>
      &lt;expiry-address>jms.queue.expiryQueue&lt;/expiry-address>
      &lt;last-value-queue>true&lt;/last-value-queue>
      &lt;max-size-bytes>100000&lt;/max-size-bytes>
      &lt;page-size-bytes>20000&lt;/page-size-bytes>
      &lt;redistribution-delay>0&lt;/redistribution-delay>
      &lt;send-to-dla-on-no-route>true&lt;/send-to-dla-on-no-route>
      &lt;address-full-policy>PAGE&lt;/address-full-policy>
      &lt;slow-consumer-threshold>-1&lt;/slow-consumer-threshold>
      &lt;slow-consumer-policy>NOTIFY&lt;/slow-consumer-policy>
      &lt;slow-consumer-check-period>5&lt;/slow-consumer-check-period>
   &lt;/address-setting>
&lt;/address-settings></programlisting>
        <para>The idea with address settings, is you can provide a block of settings which will be
            applied against any addresses that match the string in the <literal>match</literal> attribute. In the
            above example the settings would only be applied to any addresses which exactly match
            the address <literal>jms.queue.exampleQueue</literal>, but you can also use wildcards to apply sets of
            configuration against many addresses. The wildcard syntax used is described <link linkend="wildcard-syntax">here</link>.</para>
        <para>For example, if you used the <literal>match</literal> string <literal>jms.queue.#</literal> the settings would be applied
        to all addresses which start with <literal>jms.queue.</literal> which would be all JMS queues.</para>
        <para>The meaning of the specific settings are explained fully throughout the user manual, however here is a brief
            description with a link to the appropriate chapter if available. </para>
        <para><literal>max-delivery-attempts</literal> defines how many time a cancelled message can
            be redelivered before sending to the <literal>dead-letter-address</literal>. A full
            explanation can be found <link linkend="undelivered-messages.configuring"
            >here</link>.</para>
        <para><literal>redelivery-delay</literal> defines how long to wait before attempting
            redelivery of a cancelled message. see <link linkend="undelivered-messages.delay"
                >here</link>.</para>
        <para><literal>expiry-address</literal> defines where to send a message that has expired.
            see <link linkend="message-expiry.configuring">here</link>.</para>
        <para><literal>expiry-delay</literal> defines the expiration time that will be used for messages which are using
            the default expiration time (i.e. 0). For example, if <literal>expiry-delay</literal> is set to "10" and a
            message which is using the default expiration time (i.e. 0) arrives then its expiration time of "0" will be
            changed to "10." However, if a message which is using an expiration time of "20" arrives then its expiration
            time will remain unchanged. Setting <literal>expiry-delay</literal> to "-1" will disable this feature. The
            default is "-1".</para>
        <para><literal>last-value-queue</literal> defines whether a queue only uses last values or
            not. see <link linkend="last-value-queues">here</link>.</para>
        <para><literal>max-size-bytes</literal> and <literal>page-size-bytes</literal> are used to
            set paging on an address. This is explained <link linkend="paging">here</link>.</para>
        <para><literal>redistribution-delay</literal> defines how long to wait when the last
            consumer is closed on a queue before redistributing any messages. see <link
                linkend="clusters">here</link>.</para>
        <para><literal>send-to-dla-on-no-route</literal>. If a message is sent to an address, but the server does not route it to any queues,
        for example, there might be no queues bound to that address, or none of the queues have filters that match, then normally that message
        would be discarded. However if this parameter is set to true for that address, if the message is not routed to any queues it will instead
        be sent to the dead letter address (DLA) for that address, if it exists.</para>
        <para><literal>address-full-policy</literal>. This attribute can have one of the following values: PAGE, DROP, FAIL or BLOCK and determines what happens when
            an address where <literal>max-size-bytes</literal> is specified becomes full. The default value is PAGE. If the value is PAGE then further messages will be paged to disk.
            If the value is DROP then further messages will be silently dropped.
            If the value is FAIL then further messages will be dropped and an exception will be thrown on the client-side.
            If the value is BLOCK then client message producers will block when they try and send further messages.
        
        See the following chapters for more info <xref linkend="flow-control"/>, <xref linkend="paging"/>.
        </para>
       <para><literal>slow-consumer-threshold</literal>. The minimum rate of message consumption allowed before a
          consumer is considered "slow." Measured in messages-per-second. Default is -1 (i.e. disabled); any other valid
          value must be greater than 0.</para>
       <para><literal>slow-consumer-policy</literal>. What should happen when a slow consumer is detected.
          <literal>KILL</literal> will kill the consumer's connection (which will obviously impact any other client
          threads using that same connection). <literal>NOTIFY</literal> will send a CONSUMER_SLOW management
          notification which an application could receive and take action with. See
          <xref linkend="notification.types.and.headers"/> for more details on this notification.</para>
       <para><literal>slow-consumer-check-period</literal>. How often to check for slow consumers on a particular queue.
          Measured in minutes. Default is 5. See <xref linkend="slow-consumers"/> for more information about slow
          consumer detection.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
