<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<!-- Copyright © 2009 Red Hat, Inc. and others.                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- The text of and illustrations in this document are licensed by Red Hat under  -->
<!-- a Creative Commons Attribution–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license ("CC-BY-SA"). -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- An explanation of CC-BY-SA is available at                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!--            http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/.                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- In accordance with CC-BY-SA, if you distribute this document or an adaptation -->
<!-- of it, you must provide the URL for the original version.                     -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- Red Hat, as the licensor of this document, waives the right to enforce,       -->
<!-- and agrees not to assert, Section 4d of CC-BY-SA to the fullest extent        -->
<!-- permitted by applicable law.                                                  -->
<!-- ============================================================================= -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ActiveMQ_User_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="security">
    <title>Security</title>
    <para>This chapter describes how security works with ActiveMQ and how you can configure it. To
        disable security completely simply set the <literal>security-enabled</literal> property to
        false in the <literal>activemq-configuration.xml</literal> file.</para>
    <para>For performance reasons security is cached and invalidated every so long. To change this
        period set the property <literal>security-invalidation-interval</literal>, which is in
        milliseconds. The default is <literal>10000</literal> ms.</para>
    <section id="security.settings.roles">
        <title>Role based security for addresses</title>
        <para>ActiveMQ contains a flexible role-based security model for applying security to queues,
            based on their addresses.</para>
        <para>As explained in <xref linkend="using-core"/>, ActiveMQ core consists mainly of sets of
            queues bound to addresses. A message is sent to an address and the server looks up the
            set of queues that are bound to that address, the server then routes the message to
            those set of queues.</para>
        <para>ActiveMQ allows sets of permissions to be defined against the queues based on their
            address. An exact match on the address can be used or a wildcard match can be used using
            the wildcard characters '<literal>#</literal>' and '<literal>*</literal>'.</para>
        <para>Seven different permissions can be given to the set of queues which match the address.
            Those permissions are:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>createDurableQueue</literal>. This permission allows the user to
                    create a durable queue under matching addresses.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>deleteDurableQueue</literal>. This permission allows the user to
                    delete a durable queue under matching addresses.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>createNonDurableQueue</literal>. This permission allows the user to create
                    a non-durable queue under matching addresses.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>deleteNonDurableQueue</literal>. This permission allows the user to delete
                    a non-durable queue under matching addresses.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>send</literal>. This permission allows the user to send a message to
                    matching addresses.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>consume</literal>. This permission allows the user to consume a
                    message from a queue bound to matching addresses.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>manage</literal>. This permission allows the user to invoke
                    management operations by sending management messages to the management
                    address.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>For each permission, a list of roles who are granted that permission is specified. If
            the user has any of those roles, he/she will be granted that permission for that set of
            addresses.</para>
        <para>Let's take a simple example, here's a security block from <literal
                >activemq-configuration.xml</literal> or <literal>activemq-queues.xml</literal>
            file:</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;security-setting match="globalqueues.europe.#">
   &lt;permission type="createDurableQueue" roles="admin"/>
   &lt;permission type="deleteDurableQueue" roles="admin"/>
   &lt;permission type="createNonDurableQueue" roles="admin, guest, europe-users"/>
   &lt;permission type="deleteNonDurableQueue" roles="admin, guest, europe-users"/>
   &lt;permission type="send" roles="admin, europe-users"/>
   &lt;permission type="consume" roles="admin, europe-users"/>
&lt;/security-setting></programlisting>
        <para>The '<literal>#</literal>' character signifies "any sequence of words". Words are
            delimited by the '<literal>.</literal>' character. For a full description of the
            wildcard syntax please see <xref linkend="wildcard-syntax"/>. The above security block
            applies to any address that starts with the string "globalqueues.europe.":</para>
        <para>Only users who have the <literal>admin</literal> role can create or delete durable
            queues bound to an address that starts with the string "globalqueues.europe."</para>
        <para>Any users with the roles <literal>admin</literal>, <literal>guest</literal>, or
                <literal>europe-users</literal> can create or delete temporary queues bound to an
            address that starts with the string "globalqueues.europe."</para>
        <para>Any users with the roles <literal>admin</literal> or <literal>europe-users</literal>
            can send messages to these addresses or consume messages from queues bound to an address
            that starts with the string "globalqueues.europe."</para>
        <para>The mapping between a user and what roles they have is handled by the security
            manager. ActiveMQ ships with a user manager that reads user credentials from a file on
            disk, and can also plug into JAAS or JBoss Application Server security.</para>
        <para>For more information on configuring the security manager, please see <xref
                linkend="change-security-manager"/>.</para>
        <para>There can be zero or more <literal>security-setting</literal> elements in each xml
            file. Where more than one match applies to a set of addresses the <emphasis>more
                specific</emphasis> match takes precedence.</para>
        <para>Let's look at an example of that, here's another <literal>security-setting</literal>
            block:</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;security-setting match="globalqueues.europe.orders.#">
   &lt;permission type="send" roles="europe-users"/>
   &lt;permission type="consume" roles="europe-users"/>
&lt;/security-setting></programlisting>
        <para>In this <literal>security-setting</literal> block the match
            'globalqueues.europe.orders.#' is more specific than the previous match
            'globalqueues.europe.#'. So any addresses which match 'globalqueues.europe.orders.#'
            will take their security settings <emphasis>only</emphasis> from the latter
            security-setting block.</para>
        <para>Note that settings are not inherited from the former block. All the settings will be
            taken from the more specific matching block, so for the address
            'globalqueues.europe.orders.plastics' the only permissions that exist are <literal
                >send</literal> and <literal>consume</literal> for the role europe-users. The
            permissions <literal>createDurableQueue</literal>, <literal
            >deleteDurableQueue</literal>, <literal>createNonDurableQueue</literal>, <literal
                >deleteNonDurableQueue</literal> are not inherited from the other security-setting
            block.</para>
        <para>By not inheriting permissions, it allows you to effectively deny permissions in more
            specific security-setting blocks by simply not specifying them. Otherwise it would not
            be possible to deny permissions in sub-groups of addresses.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) Transport</title>
        <para>When messaging clients are connected to servers, or servers are connected to other
            servers (e.g. via bridges) over an untrusted network then ActiveMQ allows that traffic to
            be encrypted using the Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) transport.</para>
        <para>For more information on configuring the SSL transport, please see <xref
                linkend="configuring-transports"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Basic user credentials</title>
        <para>ActiveMQ ships with a security manager implementation that reads user credentials, i.e.
            user names, passwords and role information from an xml file on the classpath called
                <literal>activemq-users.xml</literal>. This is the default security manager.</para>
        <para>If you wish to use this security manager, then users, passwords and roles can easily
            be added into this file.</para>
        <para>Let's take a look at an example file:</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;configuration xmlns="urn:activemq"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="urn:activemq ../schemas/activemq-users.xsd ">

   &lt;defaultuser name="guest" password="guest">
      &lt;role name="guest"/>
   &lt;/defaultuser>

   &lt;user name="tim" password="marmite">
      &lt;role name="admin"/>
   &lt;/user>

   &lt;user name="andy" password="doner_kebab">
      &lt;role name="admin"/>
      &lt;role name="guest"/>
   &lt;/user>

   &lt;user name="jeff" password="camembert">
      &lt;role name="europe-users"/>
      &lt;role name="guest"/>
   &lt;/user>

&lt;/configuration></programlisting>
        <para>The first thing to note is the element <literal>defaultuser</literal>. This defines
            what user will be assumed when the client does not specify a username/password when
            creating a session. In this case they will be the user <literal>guest</literal> and have
            the role also called <literal>guest</literal>. Multiple roles can be specified for a
            default user.</para>
        <para>We then have three more users, the user <literal>tim</literal> has the role <literal
                >admin</literal>. The user <literal>andy</literal> has the roles <literal
                >admin</literal> and <literal>guest</literal>, and the user <literal>jeff</literal>
            has the roles <literal>europe-users</literal> and <literal>guest</literal>.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="change-security-manager">
        <title>Changing the security manager</title>
        <para>If you do not want to use the default security manager then you can specify a
            different one by editing the file <literal>activemq-beans.xml</literal> (or <literal
                >activemq-jboss-beans.xml</literal> if you're running JBoss Application Server) and
            changing the class for the <literal>ActiveMQSecurityManager</literal> bean.</para>
        <para>Let's take a look at a snippet from the default beans file:</para>
        <programlisting>           
&lt;bean name="ActiveMQSecurityManager" class="org.apache.activemq.spi.core.security.ActiveMQSecurityManagerImpl">
   &lt;start ignored="true"/>
   &lt;stop ignored="true"/>
&lt;/bean></programlisting>
        <para>The class <literal>org.apache.activemq.spi.core.security.ActiveMQSecurityManagerImpl</literal>
            is the default security manager that is used by the standalone server.</para>
        <para>ActiveMQ ships with two other security manager implementations you can use
            off-the-shelf; one a JAAS security manager and another for integrating with JBoss
            Application Sever security, alternatively you could write your own implementation by
            implementing the <literal>org.apache.activemq.spi.core.security.ActiveMQSecurityManager</literal>
            interface, and specifying the classname of your implementation in the file <literal
            >activemq-beans.xml</literal> (or <literal>activemq-jboss-beans.xml</literal> if
            you're running JBoss Application Server).</para>
        <para>These two implementations are discussed in the next two sections.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>JAAS Security Manager</title>
        <para>JAAS stands for 'Java Authentication and Authorization Service' and is a standard part
            of the Java platform. It provides a common API for security authentication and
            authorization, allowing you to plugin your pre-built implementations.</para>
        <para>To configure the JAAS security manager to work with your pre-built JAAS infrastructure
            you need to specify the security manager as a <literal>JAASSecurityManager</literal> in
            the beans file. Here's an example:</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;bean name="ActiveMQSecurityManager" class="org.apache.activemq.integration.jboss.security.JAASSecurityManager">
   &lt;start ignored="true"/>
   &lt;stop ignored="true"/>

   &lt;property name="ConfigurationName">org.apache.activemq.jms.example.ExampleLoginModule&lt;/property>
   &lt;property name="Configuration">
      &lt;inject bean="ExampleConfiguration"/>
   &lt;/property>
   &lt;property name="CallbackHandler">
      &lt;inject bean="ExampleCallbackHandler"/>
   &lt;/property>
&lt;/bean></programlisting>
        <para>Note that you need to feed the JAAS security manager with three properties:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>ConfigurationName: the name of the <literal>LoginModule</literal>
                    implementation that JAAS must use</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Configuration: the <literal>Configuration</literal> implementation used by
                    JAAS</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>CallbackHandler: the <literal>CallbackHandler</literal> implementation to use
                    if user interaction are required</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <section>
            <title>Example</title>
            <para>See <xref linkend="examples.jaas"/> for an example which shows how ActiveMQ can be
                configured to use JAAS.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>JBoss AS Security Manager</title>
        <para>The JBoss AS security manager is used when running ActiveMQ inside the JBoss
            Application server. This allows tight integration with the JBoss Application Server's
            security model.</para>
        <para>The class name of this security manager is <literal
                >org.apache.activemq.integration.jboss.security.JBossASSecurityManager</literal></para>
        <para>Take a look at one of the default <literal>activemq-jboss-beans.xml</literal> files for
            JBoss Application Server that are bundled in the distribution for an example of how this
            is configured.</para>
       <section>
          <title>Configuring Client Login</title>
          <para>JBoss can be configured to allow client login, basically this is when a JEE component such as a Servlet
             or EJB sets security credentials on the current security context  and these are used throughout the call.
             If you would like these credentials to be used by ActiveMQ when sending or consuming messages then
          set <literal>allowClientLogin</literal> to true. This will bypass ActiveMQ authentication and propagate the
          provided Security Context. If you would like ActiveMQ to authenticate using the propagated security then set the
          <literal>authoriseOnClientLogin</literal> to true also.</para>
          <para>There is more info on using the JBoss client login module <ulink
                url="http://community.jboss.org/wiki/ClientLoginModule">here</ulink> </para>
          <note><para>If messages are sent non blocking then there is a chance that these could arrive on the server after
          the calling thread has completed meaning that the security context has been cleared. If this is the case then messages
          will need to be sent blocking</para></note>
       </section>
       <section>
          <title>Changing the Security Domain</title>
          <para>The name of the security domain used by the JBoss AS security manager defaults to <literal>java:/jaas/activemq
          </literal>.  This can be changed by specifying <literal>securityDomainName</literal> (e.g. java:/jaas/myDomain).
          </para>
       </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Changing the username/password for clustering</title>
        <para>In order for cluster connections to work correctly, each node in the cluster must make
            connections to the other nodes. The username/password they use for this should always be
            changed from the installation default to prevent a security risk.</para>
        <para>Please see <xref linkend="management"/> for instructions on how to do this.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
