<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<!-- Copyright © 2009 Red Hat, Inc. and others.                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- The text of and illustrations in this document are licensed by Red Hat under  -->
<!-- a Creative Commons Attribution–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license ("CC-BY-SA"). -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- An explanation of CC-BY-SA is available at                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!--            http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/.                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- In accordance with CC-BY-SA, if you distribute this document or an adaptation -->
<!-- of it, you must provide the URL for the original version.                     -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- Red Hat, as the licensor of this document, waives the right to enforce,       -->
<!-- and agrees not to assert, Section 4d of CC-BY-SA to the fullest extent        -->
<!-- permitted by applicable law.                                                  -->
<!-- ============================================================================= -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ActiveMQ_User_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="slow-consumers">
   <title>Detecting Slow Consumers</title>
   <para>In this section we will discuss how ActiveMQ can be configured to deal with slow consumers. A slow consumer with
      a server-side queue (e.g. JMS topic subscriber) can pose a significant problem for broker performance. If messages
      build up in the consumer's server-side queue then memory will begin filling up and the broker may enter paging
      mode which would impact performance negatively. However, criteria can be set so that consumers which don't
      acknowledge messages quickly enough can potentially be disconnected from the broker which in the case of a
      non-durable JMS subscriber would allow the broker to remove the subscription and all of its messages freeing up
      valuable server resources.
   </para>
   <section id="slow.consumer.configuration">
      <title>Configuration required for detecting slow consumers</title>
      <para>By default the server will not detect slow consumers. If slow consumer detection is desired then see
      <xref linkend="queue-attributes.address-settings"/>
         for more details.
      </para>
      <para>The calculation to determine whether or not a consumer is slow only inspects the number of messages a
         particular consumer has <emphasis>acknowledged</emphasis>. It doesn't take into account whether or not flow
         control has been enabled on the consumer, whether or not the consumer is streaming a large message, etc. Keep
         this in mind when configuring slow consumer detection.
      </para>
      <para>Please note that slow consumer checks are performed using the scheduled thread pool and that each queue on
         the broker with slow consumer detection enabled will cause a new entry in the internal
         <literal>java.util.concurrent.ScheduledThreadPoolExecutor</literal> instance. If there are a high number of
         queues and the <literal>slow-consumer-check-period</literal> is relatively low then there may be delays in
         executing some of the checks. However, this will not impact the accuracy of the calculations used by the
         detection algorithm. See <xref linkend="server.scheduled.thread.pool"/> for more details about this pool.
      </para>
   </section>
</chapter>
