<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more            -->
<!-- contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with          -->
<!-- this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.           -->
<!-- The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0       -->
<!-- (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with          -->
<!-- the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at                          -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!--     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0                                -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software           -->
<!-- distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,             -->
<!-- WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.      -->
<!-- See the License for the specific language governing permissions and           -->
<!-- limitations under the License.                                                -->
<!-- ============================================================================= -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ActiveMQ_User_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="undelivered-messages">
   <title>Message Redelivery and Undelivered Messages</title>
   <para>Messages can be delivered unsuccessfully (e.g. if the transacted session used to consume
      them is rolled back). Such a message goes back to its queue ready to be redelivered. However,
      this means it is possible for a message to be delivered again and again without any success
      and remain in the queue, clogging the system.</para>
   <para>There are 2 ways to deal with these undelivered messages:</para>
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>Delayed redelivery.</para>
         <para>It is possible to delay messages redelivery to let the client some time to recover
            from transient failures and not overload its network or CPU resources</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Dead Letter Address.</para>
         <para>It is also possible to configure a dead letter address so that after a specified
            number of unsuccessful deliveries, messages are removed from the queue and will not be
            delivered again</para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>Both options can be combined for maximum flexibility.</para>
   <section>
      <title>Delayed Redelivery</title>
      <para>Delaying redelivery can often be useful in the case that clients regularly fail or
         rollback. Without a delayed redelivery, the system can get into a "thrashing" state, with
         delivery being attempted, the client rolling back, and delivery being re-attempted ad
         infinitum in quick succession, consuming valuable CPU and network resources.</para>
      <section id="undelivered-messages.delay">
         <title>Configuring Delayed Redelivery</title>
         <para>Delayed redelivery is defined in the address-setting configuration:</para>
         <programlisting>
&lt;!-- delay redelivery of messages for 5s -->
&lt;address-setting match="jms.queue.exampleQueue">
   &lt;!-- default is 1.0 --> 
   &lt;redelivery-delay-multiplier>1.5&lt;/redelivery-delay-multiplier>
   &lt;!-- default is 0 (no delay) --> 
   &lt;redelivery-delay>5000&lt;/redelivery-delay>
   &lt;!-- default is redelivery-delay * 10 -->
   &lt;max-redelivery-delay>50000&lt;/max-redelivery-delay>
 
&lt;/address-setting></programlisting>
         <para>If a <literal>redelivery-delay</literal> is specified, ActiveMQ will wait this delay
            before redelivering the messages.</para>
         <para>By default, there is no redelivery delay (<literal>redelivery-delay</literal>is set
            to 0).</para>
         <para>Other subsequent messages will be delivery regularly, only the cancelled message
               will be sent asynchronously back to the queue after the delay.</para>
         <para>You can specify a multiplier that will take effect on top of the redelivery-delay
               with a max-redelivery-delay to be taken into account.</para>
         <para>The max-redelivery-delay is defaulted to redelivery-delay * 10</para>
         <para>Address wildcards can be used to configure redelivery delay for a set of addresses
            (see <xref linkend="wildcard-syntax"/>), so you don't have to specify redelivery delay
            individually for each address.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Example</title>
         <para>See <xref linkend="examples.delayed-redelivery"/> for an example which shows how
            delayed redelivery is configured and used with JMS.</para>
      </section>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>Dead Letter Addresses</title>
      <para>To prevent a client infinitely receiving the same undelivered message (regardless of
         what is causing the unsuccessful deliveries), messaging systems define <emphasis
            role="italic">dead letter addresses</emphasis>: after a specified unsuccessful delivery
         attempts, the message is removed from the queue and send instead to a dead letter address. </para>
      <para>Any such messages can then be diverted to queue(s) where they can later be perused by
         the system administrator for action to be taken.</para>
      <para>ActiveMQ's addresses can be assigned a dead letter address. Once the messages have been
         unsuccessfully delivered for a given number of attempts, they are removed from the queue
         and sent to the dead letter address. These <emphasis>dead letter</emphasis> messages can
         later be consumed for further inspection.</para>
      <section id="undelivered-messages.configuring">
         <title>Configuring Dead Letter Addresses</title>
         <para>Dead letter address is defined in the address-setting configuration:</para>
         <programlisting>
&lt;!-- undelivered messages in exampleQueue will be sent to the dead letter address
   deadLetterQueue after 3 unsuccessful delivery attempts -->
&lt;address-setting match="jms.queue.exampleQueue">
   &lt;dead-letter-address>jms.queue.deadLetterQueue&lt;/dead-letter-address>
   &lt;max-delivery-attempts>3&lt;/max-delivery-attempts>
&lt;/address-setting></programlisting>
         <para>If a <literal>dead-letter-address</literal> is not specified, messages will removed
            after <literal>max-delivery-attempts</literal> unsuccessful attempts.</para>
         <para>By default, messages are redelivered 10 times at the maximum. Set <literal
               >max-delivery-attempts</literal> to -1 for infinite redeliveries.</para>
         <para>For example, a dead letter can be set globally for a set of matching addresses and
            you can set <literal>max-delivery-attempts</literal> to -1 for a specific address
            setting to allow infinite redeliveries only for this address.</para>
         <para>Address wildcards can be used to configure dead letter settings for a set of
            addresses (see <xref linkend="wildcard-syntax"/>).</para>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Dead Letter Properties</title>
         <para>Dead letter messages which are consumed from a dead letter address have the following
            properties:</para>
         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para><literal>_HQ_ORIG_ADDRESS</literal></para>
               <para>a String property containing the <emphasis>original address</emphasis> of
                  the dead letter message</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para><literal>_HQ_ORIG_QUEUE</literal></para>
               <para>a String property containing the <emphasis>original queue</emphasis> of
                  the dead letter message</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Example</title>
         <para>See <xref linkend="examples.dead-letter"/> for an example which shows how dead letter
            is configured and used with JMS.</para>
      </section>
   </section>
   <section id="configuring.delivery.count.persistence">
      <title>Delivery Count Persistence</title>
      <para>In normal use, ActiveMQ does not update delivery count <emphasis>persistently</emphasis>
         until a message is rolled back (i.e. the delivery count is not updated
            <emphasis>before</emphasis> the message is delivered to the consumer). In most messaging
         use cases, the messages are consumed, acknowledged and forgotten as soon as they are
         consumed. In these cases, updating the delivery count persistently before delivering the
         message would add an extra persistent step <emphasis>for each message delivered</emphasis>,
         implying a significant performance penalty.</para>
      <para>However, if the delivery count is not updated persistently before the message delivery
         happens, in the event of a server crash, messages might have been delivered but that will
         not have been reflected in the delivery count. During the recovery phase, the server will
         not have knowledge of that and will deliver the message with <literal>redelivered</literal>
         set to <literal>false</literal> while it should be <literal>true</literal>. </para>
      <para>As this behavior breaks strict JMS semantics, ActiveMQ allows to persist delivery count
         before message delivery but disabled it by default for performance implications.</para>
      <para>To enable it, set <literal>persist-delivery-count-before-delivery</literal> to <literal
            >true</literal> in <literal>activemq-configuration.xml</literal>:</para>
      <programlisting>
&lt;persist-delivery-count-before-delivery>true&lt;/persist-delivery-count-before-delivery></programlisting>
   </section>
</chapter>
