<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<!-- Copyright © 2009 Red Hat, Inc. and others.                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- The text of and illustrations in this document are licensed by Red Hat under  -->
<!-- a Creative Commons Attribution–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license ("CC-BY-SA"). -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- An explanation of CC-BY-SA is available at                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!--            http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/.                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- In accordance with CC-BY-SA, if you distribute this document or an adaptation -->
<!-- of it, you must provide the URL for the original version.                     -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- Red Hat, as the licensor of this document, waives the right to enforce,       -->
<!-- and agrees not to assert, Section 4d of CC-BY-SA to the fullest extent        -->
<!-- permitted by applicable law.                                                  -->
<!-- ============================================================================= -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "HornetQ_User_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="using-jms">
    <title>Using JMS</title>
    <para>Although HornetQ provides a JMS agnostic messaging API, many users will be more
        comfortable using JMS.</para>
    <para>JMS is a very popular API standard for messaging, and most messaging systems provide a JMS
        API. If you are completely new to JMS we suggest you follow the<ulink
            url="http://docs.oracle.com/javaee/1.3/jms/tutorial"> Sun
            JMS tutorial</ulink> - a full JMS tutorial is out of scope for this guide.</para>
    <para>HornetQ also ships with a wide range of examples, many of which demonstrate JMS API usage.
        A good place to start would be to play around with the simple JMS Queue and Topic example,
        but we also provide examples for many other parts of the JMS API. A full description of the
        examples is available in <xref linkend="examples"/>.</para>
    <para>In this section we'll go through the main steps in configuring the server for JMS and
        creating a simple JMS program. We'll also show how to configure and use JNDI, and also how
        to use JMS with HornetQ without using any JNDI.</para>
    <section>
        <title>A simple ordering system</title>
        <para>For this chapter we're going to use a very simple ordering system as our example. It is
            a somewhat contrived example because of its extreme simplicity, but it serves to
            demonstrate the very basics of setting up and using JMS.</para>
        <para>We will have a single JMS Queue called <literal>OrderQueue</literal>, and we will have
            a single <literal>MessageProducer</literal> sending an order message to the queue and a
            single <literal>MessageConsumer</literal> consuming the order message from the
            queue.</para>
        <para>The queue will be a <literal>durable</literal> queue, i.e. it will survive a server
            restart or crash. We also want to pre-deploy the queue, i.e. specify the queue in the
            server JMS configuration so it is created automatically without us having to explicitly
            create it from the client.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="using-jms.server.configuration">
        <title>JMS Server Configuration</title>
        <para>The file <literal>hornetq-jms.xml</literal> on the server classpath contains any JMS
            Queue, Topic and ConnectionFactory instances that we wish to create and make available
            to lookup via the JNDI.</para>
        <para>A JMS ConnectionFactory object is used by the client to make connections to the
            server. It knows the location of the server it is connecting to, as well as many other
            configuration parameters. In most cases the defaults will be acceptable.</para>
        <para>We'll deploy a single JMS Queue and a single JMS Connection Factory instance on the
            server for this example but there are no limits to the number of Queues, Topics and
            Connection Factory instances you can deploy from the file. Here's our
            configuration:</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;configuration xmlns="urn:activemq"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="urn:hornetq ../schemas/hornetq-jms.xsd ">
    
   &lt;connection-factory name="ConnectionFactory">
      &lt;connectors>
         &lt;connector-ref connector-name="netty"/>
      &lt;/connectors>
      &lt;entries>
         &lt;entry name="ConnectionFactory"/>
      &lt;/entries>
   &lt;/connection-factory>

   &lt;queue name="OrderQueue">
      &lt;entry name="queues/OrderQueue"/>
   &lt;/queue>
&lt;/configuration></programlisting>
        <para>We deploy one ConnectionFactory called <literal>ConnectionFactory</literal> and bind
            it in just one place in JNDI as given by the <literal>entry</literal> element.
            ConnectionFactory instances can be bound in many places in JNDI if you require. </para>
        <note>
            <para>The JMS connection factory references a <literal>connector</literal> called
                    <literal>netty</literal>. This is a reference to a connector object deployed in
                the main core configuration file <literal>hornetq-configuration.xml</literal> which
                defines the transport and parameters used to actually connect to the server.</para>
        </note>
    </section>
    <section id="using-jms.configure.factory.types">
        <title>Connection Factory Types</title>
        <para>The JMS API doc provides several connection factories for applications. HornetQ JMS users
              can choose to configure the types for their connection factories. Each connection factory
              has a <literal>signature</literal> attribute and a <literal>xa</literal> parameter, the
              combination of which determines the type of the factory. Attribute <literal>signature</literal>
              has three possible string values, i.e. <emphasis>generic</emphasis>, 
              <emphasis>queue</emphasis> and <emphasis>topic</emphasis>; <literal>xa</literal> is a boolean
              type parameter. The following table gives their configuration values for different 
              connection factory interfaces.</para>
        <table frame="topbot" id="using-jms.table.configure.factory.types">
                <title>Configuration for Connection Factory Types</title>
                <tgroup cols="3">
                    <colspec colname="signature" colnum="1"/>
                    <colspec colname="xa" colnum="2"/>
                    <colspec colname="cftype" colnum="3"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>signature</entry>
                            <entry>xa</entry>
                            <entry>Connection Factory Type</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>generic (default)</entry>
                            <entry>false (default)</entry>
                            <entry>javax.jms.ConnectionFactory</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>generic</entry>
                            <entry>true</entry>
                            <entry>javax.jms.XAConnectionFactory</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>queue</entry>
                            <entry>false</entry>
                            <entry>javax.jms.QueueConnectionFactory</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>queue</entry>
                            <entry>true</entry>
                            <entry>javax.jms.XAQueueConnectionFactory</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>topic</entry>
                            <entry>false</entry>
                            <entry>javax.jms.TopicConnectionFactory</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>topic</entry>
                            <entry>true</entry>
                            <entry>javax.jms.XATopicConnectionFactory</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>As an example, the following configures an XAQueueConnectionFactory:</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;configuration xmlns="urn:activemq"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="urn:hornetq ../schemas/hornetq-jms.xsd ">

   &lt;connection-factory name="ConnectionFactory" signature="queue">
      &lt;xa>true&lt;/xa>
      &lt;connectors>
         &lt;connector-ref connector-name="netty"/>
      &lt;/connectors>
      &lt;entries>
         &lt;entry name="ConnectionFactory"/>
      &lt;/entries>
   &lt;/connection-factory>
&lt;/configuration></programlisting>

    </section>
    <section>
        <title>JNDI configuration</title>
        <para>When using JNDI from the client side you need to specify a set of JNDI properties
            which tell the JNDI client where to locate the JNDI server, amongst other things. These
            are often specified in a file called <literal>jndi.properties</literal> on the client
            classpath, or you can specify them directly when creating the JNDI initial context. A
            full JNDI tutorial is outside the scope of this document, please see the <ulink
                url="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/jndi/tutorial">Sun JNDI tutorial</ulink>
            for more information on how to use JNDI.</para>
        <para>For talking to the JBoss JNDI Server, the jndi properties will look something like
            this:</para>
        <programlisting>
java.naming.factory.initial=org.jnp.interfaces.NamingContextFactory
java.naming.provider.url=jnp://myhost:1099
java.naming.factory.url.pkgs=org.jboss.naming:org.jnp.interfaces</programlisting>
        <para>Where <literal>myhost</literal> is the hostname or IP address of the JNDI server. 1099
            is the port used by the JNDI server and may vary depending on how you have configured
            your JNDI server.</para>
        <para>In the default standalone configuration, JNDI server ports are configured in the file
                <literal>hornetq-beans.xml</literal> by setting properties on the <literal
                >JNDIServer</literal> bean:</para>
        <programlisting>
&lt;bean name="StandaloneServer" class="org.apache.activemq.jms.server.impl.StandaloneNamingServer">
   &lt;constructor>
      &lt;parameter>
         &lt;inject bean="HornetQServer"/>
      &lt;/parameter>
   &lt;/constructor>
   &lt;property name="port">${jnp.port:1099}&lt;/property>
   &lt;property name="bindAddress">${jnp.host:localhost}&lt;/property>
   &lt;property name="rmiPort">${jnp.rmiPort:1098}&lt;/property>
   &lt;property name="rmiBindAddress">${jnp.host:localhost}&lt;/property>
&lt;/bean></programlisting>
        <note>
            <para>If you want your JNDI server to be available to non local clients make sure you
                change its bind address to something other than <literal
                >localhost</literal>!</para>
        </note>
        <note>
            <para>The JNDIServer bean must be defined <emphasis>only when HornetQ is running in
                    stand-alone mode</emphasis>. When HornetQ is integrated to JBoss Application
                Server, JBoss AS will provide a ready-to-use JNDI server without any additional
                configuration.</para>
        </note>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The code</title>
        <para>Here's the code for the example:</para>
        <para>First we'll create a JNDI initial context from which to lookup our JMS objects:</para>
        <programlisting>InitialContext ic = new InitialContext();</programlisting>
        <para>Now we'll look up the connection factory:</para>
        <programlisting>ConnectionFactory cf = (ConnectionFactory)ic.lookup("/ConnectionFactory");</programlisting>
        <para>And look up the Queue:</para>
        <programlisting>Queue orderQueue = (Queue)ic.lookup("/queues/OrderQueue");</programlisting>
        <para>Next we create a JMS connection using the connection factory:</para>
        <programlisting>Connection connection = cf.createConnection();</programlisting>
        <para>And we create a non transacted JMS Session, with AUTO_ACKNOWLEDGE acknowledge
            mode:</para>
        <programlisting>Session session = connection.createSession(false, Session.AUTO_ACKNOWLEDGE);</programlisting>
        <para>We create a MessageProducer that will send orders to the queue:</para>
        <programlisting>MessageProducer producer = session.createProducer(orderQueue);</programlisting>
        <para>And we create a MessageConsumer which will consume orders from the queue:</para>
        <programlisting>MessageConsumer consumer = session.createConsumer(orderQueue);</programlisting>
        <para>We make sure we start the connection, or delivery won't occur on it:</para>
        <programlisting>connection.start();</programlisting>
        <para>We create a simple TextMessage and send it:</para>
        <programlisting>TextMessage message = session.createTextMessage("This is an order");
producer.send(message);</programlisting>
        <para>And we consume the message:</para>
        <programlisting>TextMessage receivedMessage = (TextMessage)consumer.receive();
System.out.println("Got order: " + receivedMessage.getText());</programlisting>
        <para>It is as simple as that. For a wide range of working JMS examples please see the
            examples directory in the distribution.</para>
        <warning>
            <para>Please note that JMS connections, sessions, producers and consumers are
                    <emphasis>designed to be re-used</emphasis>.</para>
            <para>It is an anti-pattern to create new connections, sessions, producers and consumers
                for each message you produce or consume. If you do this, your application will
                perform very poorly. This is discussed further in the section on performance tuning
                    <xref linkend="perf-tuning"/>.</para>
        </warning>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Directly instantiating JMS Resources without using JNDI</title>
        <para>Although it is a very common JMS usage pattern to lookup JMS <emphasis>Administered
                Objects</emphasis> (that's JMS Queue, Topic and ConnectionFactory instances) from
            JNDI, in some cases a JNDI server is not available and you still want to use JMS, or you
            just think "Why do I need JNDI? Why can't I just instantiate these objects
            directly?"</para>
        <para>With HornetQ you can do exactly that. HornetQ supports the direct instantiation of JMS
            Queue, Topic and ConnectionFactory instances, so you don't have to use JNDI at
            all.</para>
        <para>For a full working example of direct instantiation please see the JMS examples in
                <xref linkend="examples"/>.</para>
        <para>Here's our simple example, rewritten to not use JNDI at all:</para>
        <para>We create the JMS ConnectionFactory object via the HornetQJMSClient Utility class,
            note we need to provide connection parameters and specify which transport we are using,
            for more information on connectors please see <xref linkend="configuring-transports"
            />.</para>
        <programlisting>              
TransportConfiguration transportConfiguration = new TransportConfiguration(NettyConnectorFactory.class.getName());
ConnectionFactory cf = HornetQJMSClient.createConnectionFactoryWithoutHA(JMSFactoryType.CF,transportConfiguration);</programlisting>
        <para>We also create the JMS Queue object via the HornetQJMSClient Utility class:</para>
        <programlisting>Queue orderQueue = HornetQJMSClient.createQueue("OrderQueue");</programlisting>
        <para>Next we create a JMS connection using the connection factory:</para>
        <programlisting>Connection connection = cf.createConnection();</programlisting>
        <para>And we create a non transacted JMS Session, with AUTO_ACKNOWLEDGE acknowledge
            mode:</para>
        <programlisting>Session session = connection.createSession(false, Session.AUTO_ACKNOWLEDGE);</programlisting>
        <para>We create a MessageProducer that will send orders to the queue:</para>
        <programlisting>MessageProducer producer = session.createProducer(orderQueue);</programlisting>
        <para>And we create a MessageConsumer which will consume orders from the queue:</para>
        <programlisting>MessageConsumer consumer = session.createConsumer(orderQueue);</programlisting>
        <para>We make sure we start the connection, or delivery won't occur on it:</para>
        <programlisting>connection.start();</programlisting>
        <para>We create a simple TextMessage and send it:</para>
        <programlisting>TextMessage message = session.createTextMessage("This is an order");
producer.send(message);</programlisting>
        <para>And we consume the message:</para>
        <programlisting>TextMessage receivedMessage = (TextMessage)consumer.receive();
System.out.println("Got order: " + receivedMessage.getText());</programlisting>
    </section>
    <section id="using-jms.clientid">
        <title>Setting The Client ID</title>
        <para>This represents the client id for a JMS client and is needed for creating durable
            subscriptions. It is possible to configure this on the connection factory and can be set
            via the <literal>client-id</literal> element. Any connection created by this connection
            factory will have this set as its client id.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="using-jms.dupsokbatchsize">
        <title>Setting The Batch Size for DUPS_OK </title>
        <para>When the JMS acknowledge mode is set to <literal>DUPS_OK</literal> it is possible to
            configure the consumer so that it sends acknowledgements in batches rather that one at a
            time, saving valuable bandwidth. This can be configured via the connection factory via
            the <literal>dups-ok-batch-size</literal> element and is set in bytes. The default is
            1024 * 1024 bytes = 1 MiB.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="using-jms.txbatchsize">
        <title>Setting The Transaction Batch Size</title>
        <para>When receiving messages in a transaction it is possible to configure the consumer to
            send acknowledgements in batches rather than individually saving valuable bandwidth.
            This can be configured on the connection factory via the <literal
                >transaction-batch-size</literal> element and is set in bytes. The default is 1024 *
            1024.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
